<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?><!--
  Copyright 2006 The Apache Software Foundation

  Licensed under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the "License");
  you may not use this file except in compliance with the License.
  You may obtain a copy of the License at

       http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

  Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
  distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
  WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
  See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
  limitations under the License.
--><!-- $Id$ --><!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "-//APACHE//DTD Documentation V1.3//EN" "document-v13.dtd">
<document xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <header>
    <title>Apache&#8482; FOP: PDF/X (ISO 15930)</title>
    <version>$Revision$</version>
    <authors>
      <person name="Jeremias Märki" email="jeremias@apache.org"/>
    </authors>
  </header>
  <body>
    <section id="overview">
      <title>Overview</title>
      <warning>
        Support for PDF/X is available beginning with version 0.93. This feature is new and
        may not be 100% complete, yet. Feedback is welcome.
      </warning>
      <p>
        PDF/X is a standard which faciliates prepress digital data exchange using PDF.
        Currently, only PDF/X-3:2003 is implemented out of the many different flavours of PDF/X
        profiles. PDF/X-3:2003 is documented in 
        <link href="http://www.iso.org/iso/en/CatalogueDetailPage.CatalogueDetail?CSNUMBER=39940&amp;ICS1=37&amp;ICS2=100&amp;ICS3=99">ISO 15930-6:2003(E)</link>. 
        More info on PDF/X can be found on the  
        <link href="http://www.pdfx.info/">PDF/X info site</link>.
      </p>
    </section>
    <section id="status">
      <title>Implementation Status</title>
      <p>
        <strong>PDF/X-3:2003</strong> is implemented to the degree that FOP supports 
        the creation of the elements described in ISO 15930-6. 
      </p>
      <p>
        An important restriction of the current implementation is that all normal 
        RGB colors specified in XSL-FO and SVG are left unchanged in the sRGB color
        space (XSL-FO and SVG both use sRGB as their default color space).
        There's no conversion to a CMYK color space. Although sRGB is a
        calibrated color space, its color space has a different size than a CMYK
        color space which makes the conversion a lossy conversion and can lead to
        unwanted results. Although the use of the calibrated sRGB has been promoted
        for years, print shops usually prefer to convert an sRGB PDF to CMYK prior
        to production. Until there's full CMYK support in FOP you will have to
        work closely with your print service provider to make sure you get the 
        intended result.
      </p>
      <p>
        Tests have been performed against Adobe Acrobat 7.0.7 (Preflight function).
        Note that there are bugs in Adobe Acrobat which cause false alarms if both
        PDF/A-1b and PDF/X-3:2003 are activated at the same time.
      </p>
    </section>
    <section id="command-line">
      <title>Usage (command line)</title>
      <p>
        To activate PDF/X-3:2003 from the command-line, specify "-pdfprofile PDF/X-3:2003" 
        as a parameter. If there is a violation of one of the validation rules for 
        PDF/X, an error message is presented and the processing stops.
      </p>
    </section>
    <section id="embedded">
      <title>Usage (embedded)</title>
      <p>
        When FOP is embedded in another Java application you can set a special option
        on the renderer options in the user agent to activate the PDF/A-1b profile.
        Here's an example:
      </p>
      <source xml:space="preserve"><![CDATA[
FOUserAgent userAgent = fopFactory.newFOUserAgent();
userAgent.getRendererOptions().put("pdf-x-mode", "PDF/X-3:2003");
Fop fop = fopFactory.newFop(MimeConstants.MIME_PDF, userAgent);
[..]]]></source>
      <p>
        If one of the validation rules of PDF/X is violated, an PDFConformanceException
        (descendant of RuntimeException) is thrown.
      </p>
    </section>
    <section id="rules">
      <title>PDF/X in Action</title>
      <p>
        There are a number of things that must be looked after if you activate a PDF/X
        profile. If you receive a PDFConformanceException, have a look at the following
        list (not necessarily comprehensive):
      </p>
      <ul>
        <li>
          Make sure all (!) fonts are embedded. If you use base 14 fonts (like Helvetica)
          you need to obtain a license for them and embed them like any other font.
        </li>
        <li>
          Don't use PDF encryption. PDF/X doesn't allow it.
        </li>
        <li>
          Don't use CMYK images without an ICC color profile. PDF/X doesn't allow mixing
          color spaces and FOP currently only properly supports the sRGB color space. However,
          you will need to specify an 
          <link href="configuration.html#pdf-renderer">output device profile</link>
          (usually a CMYK profile) in the configuration. sRGB won't work here since it's a 
          display device profile, not an output device profile.
        </li>
        <li>
          Don't use non-RGB colors in SVG images. Same issue as with CMYK images.
        </li>
        <li>
          Don't use EPS graphics with fo:external-graphic. Embedding EPS graphics in PDF
          is deprecated since PDF 1.4 and prohibited by PDF/X-3:2003.
        </li>
        <li>
          PDF is forced to version 1.4 if PDF/X-3:2003 is activated.
        </li>
      </ul>
    </section>
    <section id="profile-compatibility">
      <title>PDF profile compatibility</title>
      <p>
        The PDF profiles "PDF/X-3:2003" and "PDF/A-1b" are compatible and can both be 
        activated at the same time.
      </p>
    </section>
  </body>
</document>