<?xml version="1.0"?>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" version="5.0" xml:id="chapter02">
  <info>
    <title>Computer Architecture</title>
  </info>
  <section xml:id="the_cpu">
    <info>
      <title>The CPU</title>
    </info>
    <figure>
      <info>
        <title>The CPU</title>
      </info>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="chapter02/figures/computer.eps" format="EPS"/>
        </imageobject>
        <imageobject role="fo">
          <imagedata fileref="figures/computer.svg" format="SVG" scalefit="1" width="100%" contentdepth="100%"/>
        </imageobject>
        <imageobject role="html">
          <imagedata fileref="chapter02/figures/computer.png" format="PNG"/>
        </imageobject>
        <caption>
          <para>The CPU performs instructions on values held in
	      registers.  This example shows firstly setting the value
	      of R1 to 100, loading the value from memory location
	      0x100 into R2, adding the two values together and
	      placing the result in R3 and finally storing the new
	      value (110) to R4 (for further use).</para>
        </caption>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>
    <para>To greatly simplify, a computer consists of a central
    processing unit (CPU) attached to memory.  The figure above
    illustrates the general principle behind all computer
    operations.</para>
    <para>The CPU executes instructions read from memory.  There are
    two categories of instructions</para>
    <orderedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Those that <emphasis>load</emphasis> values from memory
	into registers and <emphasis>store</emphasis> values from
	registers to memory.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Those that operate on values stored in registers.  For
	example adding, subtracting multiplying or dividing the values
	in two registers, performing bitwise operations (and, or, xor,
	etc) or performing other mathematical operations (square root,
	sin, cos, tan, etc). </para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
    <para>So in the example we are simply adding 100 to a value stored
    in memory, and storing this new result back into memory.</para>
    <section>
      <info>
        <title>Branching</title>
      </info>
      <para>Apart from loading or storing, the other important
	operation of a CPU is <emphasis>branching</emphasis>.
	Internally, the CPU keeps a record of the next instruction to
	be executed in the <emphasis>instruction pointer</emphasis>.
	Usually, the instruction pointer is incremented to point to
	the next instruction sequentially; the branch instruction will
	usually check if a specific register is zero or if a flag is
	set and, if so, will modify the pointer to a different
	address.  Thus the next instruction to execute will be from a
	different part of program; this is how loops and decision
	statements work.</para>
      <para>For example, a statement like <computeroutput>if
      (x==0)</computeroutput> might be implemented by finding the
      <computeroutput>or</computeroutput> of two registers, one
      holding <computeroutput>x</computeroutput> and the other zero;
      if the result is zero the comparison is true (i.e. all bits of
      <computeroutput>x</computeroutput> were zero) and the body of
      the statement should be taken, otherwise branch past the body
      code.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <info>
        <title>Cycles</title>
      </info>
      <para>We are all familiar with the speed of the computer, given
	in Megahertz or Gigahertz (millions or thousands of millions
	cycles per second).  This is called the <emphasis>clock
	speed</emphasis> since it is the speed that an internal clock
	within the computer pulses.</para>
      <para>The pulses are used within the processor to keep it
      internally synchronised.  On each tick or pulse another
      operation can be started; think of the clock like the person
      beating the drum to keep the rower's oars in sync. </para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <info>
        <title>Fetch, Decode, Execute, Store</title>
      </info>
      <para>Executing a single instruction consists of a particular
	cycle of events; fetching, decoding, executing and
	storing.</para>
      <para>For example, to do the
	<computeroutput>add</computeroutput> instruction above the CPU
	must</para>
      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Fetch : get the instruction from memory into the
	  processor.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Decode : internally decode what it has to do (in this
	    case add).</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Execute : take the values from the registers, actually
	  add them together</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Store : store the result back into another register.
	  You might also see the term <emphasis>retiring</emphasis>
	  the instruction.</para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
      <section>
        <info>
          <title>Looking inside a CPU</title>
        </info>
        <para>Internally the CPU has many different sub components that
	perform each of the above steps, and generally they can all
	happen independently of each other.  This is analogous to a
	physical production line, where there are many stations where
	each step has a particular task to perform.  Once done it can
	pass the results to the next station and take a new input to
	work on.</para>
        <figure xml:id="inside_the_cpu">
          <info>
            <title>Inside the CPU</title>
          </info>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="chapter02/figures/block.eps" format="EPS"/>
            </imageobject>
            <imageobject role="fo">
              <imagedata fileref="figures/block.svg" format="SVG" scalefit="1" width="100%" contentdepth="100%"/>
            </imageobject>
            <imageobject role="html">
              <imagedata fileref="chapter02/figures/block.png" format="PNG"/>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
          <caption>
            <para>The CPU is made up of many different
	  sub-components, each doing a dedicated task.</para>
          </caption>
        </figure>
        <para><xref linkend="inside_the_cpu"/> shows a very
	      simple block diagram illustrating some of the main parts
	      of a modern CPU.</para>
        <para>You can see the instructions come in and are decoded by
	the processor.  The CPU has two main types of registers, those
	for <emphasis>integer</emphasis> calculations and those for
	<emphasis>floating point</emphasis> calculations.  Floating
	point is a way of representing numbers with a decimal place in
	binary form, and is handled differently within the CPU.
	<emphasis>MMX</emphasis> (multimedia extension) and
	<emphasis>SSE</emphasis> (Streaming Single Instruction
	Multiple Data) or <emphasis>Altivec</emphasis> registers are
	similar to floating point registers.</para>
        <para>A <emphasis>register file</emphasis> is the collective
	name for the registers inside the CPU.  Below that we have the
	parts of the CPU which really do all the work.</para>
        <para>We said that processors are either loading or storing a
	value into a register or from a register into memory, or doing
	some operation on values in registers.</para>
        <para>The <emphasis>Arithmetic Logic Unit</emphasis> (ALU) is
	the heart of the CPU operation.  It takes values in registers
	and performs any of the multitude of operations the CPU is
	capable of.  All modern processors have a number of ALUs so
	each can be working independently.  In fact, processors such
	as the Pentium have both <emphasis>fast</emphasis> and
	<emphasis>slow</emphasis> ALUs; the fast ones are smaller (so
	you can fit more on the CPU) but can do only the most common
	operations, slow ALUs can do all operations but are
	bigger.</para>
        <para>The <emphasis>Address Generation Unit</emphasis> (AGU)
	handles talking to cache and main memory to get values into
	the registers for the ALU to operate on and get values out of
	registers back into main memory.</para>
        <para>Floating point registers have the same concepts, but use
	slightly different terminology for their components.</para>
      </section>
      <section>
        <info>
          <title>Pipelining</title>
        </info>
        <para>As we can see above, whilst the ALU is adding registers
	together is completely separate to the AGU writing values back
	to memory, so there is no reason why the CPU can not be doing
	both at once.  We also have multiple ALUs in the system, each
	which can be working on separate instructions.  Finally the
	CPU could be doing some floating point operations with its
	floating point logic whilst integer instructions are in flight
	too.  This process is called
	<emphasis>pipelining</emphasis><footnote><para>In fact, any
	modern processor has many more than four stages it can
	pipeline, above we have only shown a very simplified view.
	The more stages that can be executed at the same time, the
	deeper the pipeline.</para></footnote>, and a processor that
	can do this is referred to as a <emphasis>superscalar
	architecture</emphasis>.  All modern processors are
	superscalar.</para>
        <para>Another analogy might be to think of the pipeline like a
      hose that is being filled with marbles, except our marbles are
      instructions for the CPU.  Ideally you will be putting your
      marbles in one end, one after the other (one per clock pulse),
      filling up the pipe.  Once full, for each marble (instruction)
      you push in all the others will move to the next position and
      one will fall out the end (the result).</para>
        <para>Branch instruction play havoc with this model however,
	since they may or may not cause execution to start from a
	different place.  If you are pipelining, you will have to
	basically guess which way the branch will go, so you know
	which instructions to bring into the pipeline.  If the CPU has
	predicted correctly, everything goes
	fine!<footnote><para>Processors such as the Pentium use a
	<emphasis>trace cache</emphasis> to keep a track of which way
	branches are going.  Much of the time it can predict which way
	a branch will go by remembering its previous result.  For
	example, in a loop that happens 100 times, if you remember the
	last result of the branch you will be right 99 times, since
	only the last time will you actually continue with the
	program.</para></footnote> Conversely, if the processor has
	predicted incorrectly it has wasted a lot of time and has to
	clear the pipeline and start again.</para>
        <para>This process is usually referred to as a
      <emphasis>pipeline flush</emphasis> and is analogous to having
      to stop and empty out all your marbles from your hose!</para>
        <section>
          <info>
            <title>Branch Prediction</title>
          </info>
          <para>pipeline flush, predict taken, predict not taken,
	  branch delay slots</para>
        </section>
      </section>
      <section>
        <info>
          <title>Reordering</title>
        </info>
        <para>In fact, if the CPU is the hose, it is free to reorder
	the marbles within the hose, as long as they pop out the end
	in the same order you put them in.  We call this
	<emphasis>program order</emphasis> since this is the order
	that instructions are given in the computer program.</para>
        <figure xml:id="reorder_buffer">
          <info>
            <title>Reorder buffer example</title>
          </info>
          <mediaobject>
            <textobject>
              <programlisting>
1: r3 = r1 * r2
2: r4 = r2 + r3
3: r7 = r5 * r6
4: r8 = r1 + r7</programlisting>
            </textobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>
        <para>Consider an instruction stream such as that shown in
	<xref linkend="reorder_buffer"/>
	  Instruction 2 needs to wait for instruction 1 to
	complete fully before it can start.  This means that the
	pipeline has to <emphasis>stall</emphasis> as it waits for the
	value to be calculated.  Similarly instructions 3 and 4 have a
	dependency on <emphasis>r7</emphasis>.  However, instructions
	2 and 3 have no <emphasis>dependency</emphasis> on each other
	at all; this means they operate on completely separate
	registers.  If we swap instructions 2 and 3 we can get a much
	better ordering for the pipeline since the processor can be
	doing useful work rather than waiting for the pipeline to
	complete to get the result of a previous instruction.</para>
        <para>However, when writing very low level code some
	instructions may require some security about how operations
	are ordered.  We call this requirement <emphasis>memory
	semantics</emphasis>.  If you require
	<emphasis>acquire</emphasis> semantics this means that for
	this instruction you must ensure that the results of all
	previous instructions have been completed.  If you require
	<emphasis>release</emphasis> semantics you are saying that all
	instructions after this one must see the current result.
	Another even stricter semantic is a <emphasis>memory
	barrier</emphasis> or <emphasis>memory fence</emphasis> which
	requires that operations have been committed to memory before
	continuing.</para>
        <para>On some architectures these semantics are guaranteed for
	you by the processor, whilst on others you must specify them
	explicitly.  Most programmers do not need to worry directly
	about them, although you may see the terms.</para>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section>
      <info>
        <title>CISC v RISC</title>
      </info>
      <para>A common way to divide computer architectures is into
      <emphasis>Complex Instruction Set Computer</emphasis> (CISC) and
      <emphasis>Reduced Instruction Set Computer</emphasis>
      (RISC).</para>
      <para>Note in the first example, we have explicitly loaded
      values into registers, performed an addition and stored the
      result value held in another register back to memory.  This is
      an example of a RISC approach to computing -- only performing
      operations on values in registers and explicitly loading and
      storing values to and from memory.</para>
      <para>A CISC approach may be only a single instruction taking
      values from memory, performing the addition internally and
      writing the result back.  This means the instruction may take
      many cycles, but ultimately both approaches achieve the same
      goal.</para>
      <para>All modern architectures would be considered RISC
      architectures<footnote><para>Even the most common architecture,
      the Intel Pentium, whilst having an instruction set that is
      categorised as CISC, internally breaks down instructions to RISC
      style sub-instructions inside the chip before
      executing.</para></footnote>.</para>
      <para>There are a number of reasons for this</para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Whilst RISC makes assembly programming becomes more
	  complex, since virtually all programmers use high level
	  languages and leave the hard work of producing assembly
	  code to the compiler, so the other advantages outweigh this
	  disadvantage.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Because the instructions in a RISC processor are much
	  more simple, there is more space inside the chip for
	  registers.  As we know from the memory hierarchy, registers
	  are the fastest type of memory and ultimately all
	  instructions must be performed on values held in registers,
	  so all other things being equal more registers leads to
	  higher performance.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Since all instructions execute in the same time,
	  pipelining is possible.  We know pipelining requires streams
	  of instructions being constantly fed into the processor, so
	  if some instructions take a very long time and others do
	  not, the pipeline becomes far to complex to be
	  effective.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <section>
        <info>
          <title>EPIC</title>
        </info>
        <para>The Itanium processor, which is used in many example
	through this book, is an example of a modified architecture
	called Explicitly Parallel Instruction Computing.</para>
        <para>We have discussed how superscaler processors have
	pipelines that have many instructions in flight at the same
	time in different parts of the processor.  Obviously for this
	to work as well as possible instructions should be given the
	processor in an order that can make best use of the
	available elements of the CPU.</para>
        <para>Traditionally organising the incoming instruction stream
	has been the job of the hardware.  Instructions are issued by
	the program in a sequential manner; the processor must look
	ahead and try to make decisions about how to organise the
	incoming instructions.</para>
        <para>The theory behind EPIC is that there is more information
        available at higher levels which can make these decisions
        better than the processor.  Analysing a stream of assembly
        language instructions, as current processors do, loses a lot
        of information that the programmer may have provided in the
        original source code.  Think of it as the difference between
        studying a Shakespeare play and reading the Cliff's Notes
        version of the same.  Both give you the same result, but the
        original has all sorts of extra information that sets the
        scene and gives you insight into the characters.</para>
        <para>Thus the logic of ordering instructions can be moved
	from the processor to the compiler.  This means that compiler
	writers need to be smarter to try and find the best ordering
	of code for the processor.  The processor is also
	significantly simplified, since a lot of its work has been
	moved to the compiler.<footnote><para>Another term often used
	around EPIC is Very Long Instruction World (VLIW), which is
	where each instruction to the processor is extended to tell
	the processor about where it should execute the instruction in
	its internal units.  The problem with this approach is that
	code is then completely dependent on the model of processor is
	has been compiled for.  Companies are always making revisions
	to hardware, and making customers recompile their application
	every single time, and maintain a range of different binaries
	was impractical.</para><para>EPIC solves this in the usual
	computer science manner by adding a layer of abstraction.
	Rather than explicitly specifying the exact part of the
	processor the instructions should execute on, EPIC creates a
	simplified view with a few core units like memory, integer and
	floating point.</para></footnote></para>
      </section>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="memory">
    <info>
      <title>Memory</title>
    </info>
    <section>
      <info>
        <title>Memory Hierarchy</title>
      </info>
      <para>The CPU can only directly fetch instructions and data
	from cache memory, located directly on the processor chip.
	Cache memory must be loaded in from the main system memory
	(the Random Access Memory, or RAM).  RAM however, only retains
	its contents when the power is on, so needs to be stored on
	more permanent storage.</para>
      <para>We call these layers of memory the <emphasis>memory
      hierarchy</emphasis></para>
      <table>
        <info>
          <title>Memory Hierarchy</title>
        </info>
        <tgroup cols="3">
          <thead>
            <row>
              <entry>Speed</entry>
              <entry>Memory</entry>
              <entry>Description</entry>
            </row>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>Fastest</entry>
              <entry>Cache</entry>
              <entry>Cache memory is memory actually embedded inside
		the CPU.  Cache memory is very fast, typically taking
		only once cycle to access, but since it is embedded
		directly into the CPU there is a limit to how big it
		can be.  In fact, there are several sub-levels of
		cache memory (termed L1, L2, L3) all with slightly
		increasing speeds.</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry/>
              <entry>RAM</entry>
              <entry>All instructions and storage addresses for the
		processor must come from RAM.  Although RAM is very
		fast, there is still some significant time taken for
		the CPU to access it (this is termed
		<emphasis>latency</emphasis>). RAM is stored in
		separate, dedicated chips attached to the motherboard,
		meaning it is much larger than cache memory.
		</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>Slowest</entry>
              <entry>Disk</entry>
              <entry>We are all familiar with software arriving on a
		floppy disk or CDROM, and saving our files to the hard
		disk.  We are also familiar with the long time a
		program can take to load from the hard disk -- having
		physical mechanisms such as spinning disks and moving
		heads means disks are the slowest form of storage.
		But they are also by far the largest form of
		storage.</entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </table>
      <para>The important point to know about the memory hierarchy is
      the trade offs between speed and size &#x2014; the faster the
      memory the smaller it is.  Of course, if you can find a way to
      change this equation, you'll end up a billionaire!</para>
      <para>The reason caches are effective is because computer code
        generally exhibits two forms of locality<indexterm xml:id="locality"><primary>locality</primary></indexterm>
	<orderedlist><listitem><para><emphasis>Spatial</emphasis> locality suggests that
	    data within blocks is likely to be accessed together.</para></listitem><listitem><para><emphasis>Temporal</emphasis> locality suggests that
	    data that was used recently will likely be used again
	    shortly.</para></listitem></orderedlist>
	This means that benefits are gained by implementing as much
	quickly accessible memory (temporal) storing small blocks of
	relevant information (spatial) as practically possible.
        </para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="cache_in_depth">
      <info>
        <title>Cache in depth</title>
      </info>
      <para>Cache is one of the most important elements of the CPU
	  architecture.  To write efficient code developers need to
	  have an understanding of how the cache in their systems
	  works.</para>
      <para>The cache is a very fast copy of the slower main system
      memory.  Cache is much smaller than main memories because it is
      included inside the processor chip alongside the registers and
      processor logic.  This is prime real estate in computing terms,
      and there are both economic and physical limits to its maximum
      size.  As manufacturers find more and more ways to cram more and
      more transistors onto a chip cache sizes grow considerably, but
      even the largest caches are tens of megabytes, rather than the
      gigabytes of main memory or terabytes of hard disk otherwise
      common.</para>
      <para>The cache is made up of small chunks of mirrored main
	memory.  The size of these chunks is called the <emphasis>line
	size</emphasis>, and is typically something like 32 or 64
	bytes.  When talking about cache, it is very common to talk
	about the line size, or a cache line, which refers to one
	chunk of mirrored main memory.  The cache can only load and
	store memory in sizes a multiple of a cache line.</para>
      <para>Caches have their own hierarchy, commonly termed L1, L2
	and L3.  L1 cache is the fastest and smallest; L2 is bigger
	and slower, and L3 more so.</para>
      <para>L1 caches are generally further split into instruction
	  caches and data, known as the "Harvard Architecture" after
	  the relay based Harvard Mark-1 computer which introduced it.
	  Split caches help to reduce pipeline bottlenecks as earlier
	  pipeline stages tend to reference the instruction cache and
	  later stages the data cache.  Apart from reducing contention
	  for a shared resource, providing separate caches for
	  instructions also allows for alternate implementations which
	  may take advantage of the nature of instruction streaming;
	  they are read-only so do not need expensive on-chip features
	  such as multi-porting, nor need to handle handle sub-block
	  reads because the instruction stream generally uses more
	  regular sized accesses.</para>
      <figure xml:id="cache_associativity">
        <info>
          <title>Cache Associativity</title>
        </info>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="chapter02/figures/sets.eps" format="EPS"/>
          </imageobject>
          <imageobject role="fo">
            <imagedata fileref="figures/sets.svg" format="SVG" scalefit="1" width="100%" contentdepth="100%"/>
          </imageobject>
          <imageobject role="html">
            <imagedata fileref="chapter02/figures/sets.png" format="PNG"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
        <caption>
          <para>
	    A given cache line may find a valid home in one
	    of the shaded entries.</para>
        </caption>
      </figure>
      <para>During normal operation the processor is constantly
	      asking the cache to check if a particular address is
	      stored in the cache, so the cache needs some way to very
	      quickly find if it has a valid line present or not. If a
	      given address can be cached anywhere within the cache,
	      every cache line needs to be searched every time a
	      reference is made to determine a hit or a miss. To keep
	      searching fast this is done in parallel in the cache
	      hardware, but searching every entry is generally far too
	      expensive to implement for a reasonable sized cache.
	      Thus the cache can be made simpler by enforcing limits
	      on where a particular address must live.  This is a
	      trade-off; the cache is obviously much, much smaller
	      than the system memory, so some addresses must
	      <emphasis>alias</emphasis> others. If two addresses
	      which alias each other are being constantly updated they
	      are said to <emphasis>fight</emphasis> over the cache
	      line.  Thus we can categorise caches into three general
	      types, illustrated in <xref linkend="cache_associativity"/>.

	  <itemizedlist><listitem><para><emphasis>Direct mapped</emphasis> caches will allow a
	      cache line to exist only in a singe entry in the
	      cache. This is the simplest to implement in hardware,
	      but as illustrated in <xref linkend="cache_associativity"/> there is no
	      potential to avoid aliasing because the two shaded
	      addresses must share the same cache line.
	      </para></listitem><listitem><para><emphasis>Fully Associative</emphasis> caches will allow
	      a cache line to exist in any entry of the cache. This
	      avoids the problem with aliasing, since any entry is
	      available for use. But it is very expensive to implement
	      in hardware because every possible location must be
	      looked up simultaneously to determine if a value is in
	      the cache.
	      </para></listitem><listitem><para><emphasis>Set Associative</emphasis> caches are a hybrid
	      of direct and fully associative caches, and allow a
	      particular cache value to exist in some subset of the
	      lines within the cache. The cache is divided into even
	      compartments called <emphasis>ways</emphasis>, and a
	      particular address could be located in any way. Thus an
	      <emphasis>n</emphasis>-way set associative cache will
	      allow a cache line to exist in any entry of a set sized
	      total blocks mod n &#x2014; <xref linkend="cache_associativity"/> shows a sample
	      8-element, 4-way set associative cache; in this case the
	      two addresses have four possible locations, meaning only
	      half the cache must be searched upon lookup.  The more
	      ways, the more possible locations and the less aliasing,
	      leading to overall better performance.
	      </para></listitem></itemizedlist>
	</para>
      <para>Once the cache is full the processor needs to get rid of
	a line to make room for a new line.  There are many algorithms
	by which the processor can choose which line to evict; for
	example <emphasis>least recently used</emphasis> (LRU) is an
	algorithm where the oldest unused line is discarded to make
	room for the new line.</para>
      <para>When data is only read from the cache there is no need
	to ensure consistency with main memory.  However, when the
	processor starts writing to cache lines it needs to make some
	decisions about how to update the underlying main memory.  A
	<emphasis>write-through</emphasis> cache will write the
	changes directly into the main system memory as the processor
	updates the cache.  This is slower since the process of
	writing to the main memory is, as we have seen, slower.
	Alternatively a <emphasis>write-back</emphasis> cache delays
	writing the changes to RAM until absolutely necessary.  The
	obvious advantage is that less main memory access is
	required when cache entries are written.  Cache lines that
	have been written but not committed to memory are referred to
	as <emphasis>dirty</emphasis>.  The disadvantage is that when
	a cache entry is evicted, it may require two memory accesses
	(one to write dirty data main memory, and another to load the
	new data).</para>
      <para>If an entry exists in both a higher-level and lower-level
	cache at the same time, we say the higher-level cache is
	<emphasis>inclusive</emphasis>. Alternatively, if the
	higher-level cache having a line removes the possibility of a
	lower level cache having that line, we say it is
	<emphasis>exclusive</emphasis>.  This choice is discussed
	further in <xref linkend="cache_exclusivity_in_smp"/>.
      </para>
      <section>
        <info>
          <title>Cache Addressing</title>
        </info>
        <para>So far we have not discussed how a cache decides if a
	  given address resides in the cache or not.  Clearly, caches
	  must keep a directory of what data currently resides in the
	  cache lines. The cache directory and data may co-located on
	  the processor, but may also be separate &#x2014; such as in
	  the case of the POWER5 processor which has an on-core L3
	  directory, but actually accessing the data requires
	  traversing the L3 bus to access off-core memory. An
	  arrangement like this can facilitate quicker hit/miss
	  processing without the other costs of keeping the entire
	  cache on-core.
	</para>
        <figure xml:id="cache_tags">
          <info>
            <title>Cache tags</title>
          </info>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="chapter02/figures/tags.eps" format="EPS"/>
            </imageobject>
            <imageobject role="fo">
              <imagedata fileref="figures/tags.svg" format="SVG" scalefit="1" width="100%" contentdepth="100%"/>
            </imageobject>
            <imageobject role="html">
              <imagedata fileref="chapter02/figures/tags.png" format="PNG"/>
            </imageobject>
            <caption>
              <para>Tags need to be checked in parallel to keep
latency times low; more tag bits (i.e. less set associativity)
requires more complex hardware to achieve this. Alternatively more set
associativity means less tags, but the processor now needs hardware to
multiplex the output of the many sets, which can also add latency.
</para>
            </caption>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>
        <para>To quickly decide if an address lies within the cache it
	  is separated into three parts; the <emphasis>tag</emphasis>
	  and the <emphasis>index</emphasis> and the
	  <emphasis>offset</emphasis>.</para>
        <para>The offset bits depend on the line size of the cache.
	  For example, a 32-byte line size would use the last 5-bits
	  (i.e. 2<superscript>5</superscript>) of the address as the
	  offset into the line.</para>
        <para>The <emphasis>index</emphasis> is the particular cache
	line that an entry may reside in.  As an example, let us
	consider a cache with 256 entries.  If this is a direct-mapped
	cache, we know the data may reside in only one possible line,
	so the next 8-bits (2<superscript>8</superscript>) after the
	offset describe the line to check - between 0 and 255.</para>
        <para>Now, consider the same 256 element cache, but divided
	into two ways.  This means there are two groups of 128 lines,
	and the given address may reside in either of these groups.
	Consequently only 7-bits are required as an index to offset
	into the 128-entry ways.  For a given cache size, as we
	increase the number of ways, we decrease the number of bits
	required as an index since each way gets smaller.</para>
        <para>The cache directory still needs to check if the
	particular address stored in the cache is the one it is
	interested in.  Thus the remaining bits of the address are the
	<emphasis>tag</emphasis> bits which the cache directory checks
	against the incoming address tag bits to determine if there is
	a cache hit or not.  This relationship is illustrated in <xref linkend="cache_tags"/>.</para>
        <para>When there are multiple ways, this check must happen in
	parallel within each way, which then passes its result into a
	multiplexor which outputs a final <emphasis>hit</emphasis> or
	<emphasis>miss</emphasis> result.  As describe above, the more
	associative a cache is, the less bits are required for index
	and the more as tag bits &#x2014; to the extreme of a
	fully-associative cache where no bits are used as index bits.
	The parallel matching of tags bits is the expensive component
	of cache design and generally the limiting factor on how many
	lines (i.e, how big) a cache may grow.</para>
      </section>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="peripherals">
    <info>
      <title>Peripherals and buses</title>
    </info>
    <para>Peripherals are any of the many external devices that
      connect to your computer.  Obviously, the processor must have
      some way of talking to the peripherals to make them
      useful.</para>
    <para>The communication channel between the processor and the
      peripherals is called a <emphasis>bus</emphasis>.</para>
    <section>
      <info>
        <title>Peripheral Bus concepts</title>
      </info>
      <para>A device requires both input and output to be useful.
      There are a number of common concepts required for useful
      communication with peripherals.</para>
      <section>
        <info>
          <title>Interrupts</title>
        </info>
        <para>An interrupt allows the device to literally interrupt
	  the processor to flag some information.  For example, when a
	  key is pressed, an interrupt is generated to deliver the
	  key-press event to the operating system.  Each device is
	  assigned an interrupt by some combination of the operating
	  system and BIOS.</para>
        <para>Devices are generally connected to an
	<emphasis>programmable interrupt controller</emphasis> (PIC),
	a separate chip that is part of the motherboard which buffers
	and communicates interrupt information to the main processor.
	Each device has a physical <emphasis>interrupt line</emphasis>
	between it an one of the PIC's provided by the system.  When
	the device wants to interrupt, it will modify the voltage on
	this line.</para>
        <para>A very broad description of the PIC's role is that it
	receives this interrupt and converts it to a message for
	consumption by the main processor.  While the exact procedure
	varies by architecture, the general principle is that the
	operating system has configured an <emphasis>interrupt
	descriptor table</emphasis> which pairs each of the possible
	interrupts with a code address to jump to when the interrupt
	is received.  This is illustrated in <xref linkend="interrupt_handling"/>.</para>
        <para>Writing this <emphasis>interrupt handler</emphasis> is
	the job of the device driver author in conjunction with the
	operating system.</para>
        <figure xml:id="interrupt_handling">
          <info>
            <title>Overview of handling an interrupt</title>
          </info>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="chapter02/figures/interrupt.eps" format="EPS"/>
            </imageobject>
            <imageobject role="fo">
              <imagedata fileref="figures/interrupt.svg" format="SVG" scalefit="1" width="100%" contentdepth="100%"/>
            </imageobject>
            <imageobject role="html">
              <imagedata fileref="chapter02/figures/interrupt.png" format="PNG"/>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
          <caption>
            <para>A generic overview of handling an interrupt.  The
	    device raises the interrupt to the interrupt controller,
	    which passes the information onto the processor.  The
	    processor looks at its descriptor table, filled out by the
	    operating system, to find the code to handle the
	    fault.</para>
          </caption>
        </figure>
        <para>Most drivers will split up handling of interrupts into
	<emphasis>bottom</emphasis> and <emphasis>top</emphasis>
	halves.  The bottom half will acknowledge the interrupt, queue
	actions for processing and return the processor to what it was
	doing quickly.  The top half will then run later when the CPU
	is free and do the more intensive processing.  This is to stop
	an interrupt hogging the entire CPU.</para>
        <section>
          <info>
            <title>Saving state</title>
          </info>
          <para>Since an interrupt can happen at any time, it is
	  important that you can return to the running operation when
	  finished handling the interrupt.  It is generally the job of
	  the operating system to ensure that upon entry to the
	  interrupt handler, it saves any <emphasis>state</emphasis>;
	  i.e. registers, and restores them when returning from the
	  interrupt handler.  In this way, apart from some lost time,
	  the interrupt is completely transparent to whatever happens
	  to be running at the time.</para>
        </section>
        <section>
          <info>
            <title>Interrupts v traps and exceptions</title>
          </info>
          <para>While an interrupt is generally associated with an
	  external event from a physical device, the same mechanism is
	  useful for handling internal system operations.  For
	  example, if the processor detects conditions such as an
	  access to invalid memory, an attempt to divide-by-zero or an
	  invalid instruction, it can internally raise an
	  <emphasis>exception</emphasis> to be handled by the
	  operating system.  It is also the mechanism used to trap
	  into the operating system for <emphasis>system
	  calls</emphasis>, as discussed in <xref linkend="system_calls"/> and to implement virtual
	  memory, as discussed in <xref linkend="chapter05"/>.
	  Although generated internally rather than from an external
	  source, the principles of asynchronously interrupting the
	  running code remains the same.</para>
        </section>
        <section>
          <info>
            <title>Types of interrupts</title>
          </info>
          <para>There are two main ways of signalling interrupts on a
	    line &#x2014; <emphasis>level</emphasis> and
	    <emphasis>edge</emphasis> triggered.</para>
          <para>Level-triggered interrupts define voltage of the
	  interrupt line being held high to indicate an interrupt is
	  pending.  Edge-triggered interrupts detect
	  <emphasis>transitions</emphasis> on the bus; that is when
	  the line voltage goes from low to high.  With an
	  edge-triggered interrupt, a square-wave pulse is detected by
	  the PIC as signalling and interrupt has been raised.</para>
          <para>The difference is pronounced when devices share an
	  interrupt line.  In a level-triggered system, the interrupt
	  line will be high until all devices that have raised an
	  interrupt have been processed and un-asserted their
	  interrupt.</para>
          <para>In an edge-triggered system, a pulse on the line will
	  indicate to the PIC that an interrupt has occurred, which it
	  will signal to the operating system for handling.  However,
	  if further pulses come in on the already asserted line from
	  another device.</para>
          <para>The issue with level-triggered interrupts is that it
	  may require some considerable amount of time to handle an
	  interrupt for a device.  During this time, the interrupt
	  line remains high and it is not possible to determine if any
	  other device has raised an interrupt on the line.  This
	  means there can be considerable unpredictable latency in
	  servicing interrupts.</para>
          <para>With edge-triggered interrupts, a long-running
	  interrupt can be noticed and queued, but other devices
	  sharing the line can still transition (and hence raise
	  interrupts) while this happens.  However, this introduces
	  new problems; if two devices interrupt at the same time it
	  may be possible to miss one of the interrupts, or
	  environmental or other interference may create a
	  <emphasis>spurious</emphasis> interrupt which should be
	  ignored.</para>
        </section>
        <section>
          <info>
            <title>Non-maskable interrupts</title>
          </info>
          <para>It is important for the system to be able to
	  <emphasis>mask</emphasis> or prevent interrupts at certain
	  times.  Generally, it is possible to put interrupts on hold,
	  but a particular class of interrupts, called
	  <emphasis>non-maskable interrupts</emphasis> (NMI), are the
	  exception to this rule.  The typical example is the
	  <emphasis>reset</emphasis> interrupt.</para>
          <para>NMIs can be useful for implementing things such as a
	  system watchdog, where a NMI is raised periodically and sets
	  some flag that must be acknowledged by the operating system.
	  If the acknowledgement is not seen before the next periodic
	  NMI, then system can be considered to be not making forward
	  progress.  Another common usage is for profiling a system.
	  A periodic NMI can be raised and used to evaluate what code
	  the processor is currently running; over time this builds a
	  profile of what code is being run and create a very useful
	  insight into system performance.</para>
        </section>
      </section>
      <section>
        <info>
          <title>IO Space</title>
        </info>
        <para>Obviously the processor will need to communicate with
	the peripheral device, and it does this via IO operations.
	The most common form of IO is so called <emphasis>memory
	mapped IO</emphasis> where registers on the device are
	<emphasis>mapped</emphasis> into memory.</para>
        <para>This means that to communicate with the device, you need
	simply read or write to a specific address in memory.  TODO:
	expand</para>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section>
      <info>
        <title>DMA</title>
      </info>
      <para>Since the speed of devices is far below the speed of processors,
    there needs to be some way to avoid making the CPU wait around
    for data from devices.</para>
      <para>Direct Memory Access (DMA) is a method of transferring
	data directly between an peripheral and system RAM.</para>
      <para>The driver can setup a device to do a DMA transfer by
	giving it the area of RAM to put its data into.  It can then
	start the DMA transfer and allow the CPU to continue with
	other tasks.</para>
      <para>Once the device is finished, it will raise an interrupt
	and signal to the driver the transfer is complete.  From this
	time the data from the device (say a file from a disk, or
	frames from a video capture card) is in memory and ready to be
	used.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <info>
        <title>Other Buses</title>
      </info>
      <para>Other buses connect between the PCI bus and external
	devices.</para>
      <section>
        <info>
          <title>USB</title>
        </info>
        <para>From an operating system point of view, a USB device is
	a group of end-points grouped together into an interface. An
	end-point can be either <emphasis>in</emphasis> or
	<emphasis>out</emphasis> and hence transfers data in one
	direction only. End-points can have a number of different
	types:</para>
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis>Control</emphasis> end-points are for
	    configuring the device, etc.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis>Interrupt</emphasis> end-points are for
	    transferring small amounts of data. They have higher
	    priority than ...</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis>Bulk</emphasis> end-points, which transfer
	    large amounts of data but do not get guaranteed time
	    constraints.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis>Isochronous</emphasis> transfers are
	    high-priority real-time transfers, but if they are missed
	    they are not re-tried. This is for streaming data like
	    video or audio where there is no point sending data again.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        <para>There can be many interfaces (made of multiple
	end-points) and interfaces are grouped into
	<emphasis>configurations</emphasis>.  However most devices
	only have a single configuration.</para>
        <figure xml:id="uhci">
          <info>
            <title>Overview of a UHCI controller operation</title>
          </info>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="chapter02/images/uhci.eps" format="EPS"/>
            </imageobject>
            <imageobject role="fo">
              <imagedata fileref="images/uhci.svg" format="SVG" scalefit="1" width="100%" contentdepth="100%"/>
            </imageobject>
            <imageobject role="html">
              <imagedata fileref="chapter02/images/uhci.png" format="PNG"/>
            </imageobject>
            <caption>
              <para>An overview of a UCHI controller, taken
  from <link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://download.intel.com/technology/usb/UHCI11D.pdf">Intel
  documentation</link>.</para>
            </caption>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>
        <para><xref linkend="uhci"/> shows an overview of a
	universal host controller interface, or UHCI.  It provides an
	overview of how USB data is moved out of the system by a
	combination of hardware and software.  Essentially, the
	software sets up a template of data in a specified format for
	the host controller to read and send across the USB
	bus.</para>
        <para>Starting at the top-left of the overview, the controller
	has a <emphasis>frame</emphasis> register with a counter which
	is incremented periodically &#x2014; every millisecond.  This
	value is used to index into a <emphasis>frame list</emphasis>
	created by software.  Each entry in this table points to a
	queue of <emphasis>transfer descriptors</emphasis>.  Software
	sets up this data in memory, and it is read by the host
	controller which is a separate chip that drives the USB bus.
	Software needs to schedule the work queues so that 90% of a
	frame time is given to isochronous data, and 10% left for
	interrupt, control and bulk data..</para>
        <para>As you can see from the diagram, the way the data is
	linked means that transfer descriptors for isochronous data
	are associated with only one particular frame pointer &#x2014;
	in other words only one particular time period &#x2014; and
	after that will be discarded.  However, the interrupt, control
	and bulk data are all <emphasis>queued</emphasis> after the
	isochronous data and thus if not transmitted in one frame
	(time period) will be done in the next.</para>
        <para>The USB layer communicates through USB <emphasis>request
	blocks</emphasis>, or URBs. A URB contains information about
	what end-point this request relates to, data, any related
	information or attributes and a call-back function to be
	called when the URB is complete. USB drivers submit URBs in a
	fixed format to the USB core, which manages them in
	co-ordination with the USB host controller as above. Your data
	gets sent off to the USB device by the USB core, and when its
	done your call-back is triggered.</para>
      </section>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="small_to_big_systems">
    <info>
      <title>Small to big systems</title>
    </info>
    <para>As Moore's law has predicted, computing power has been
    growing at a furious pace and shows no signs of slowing down.  It
    is relatively uncommon for any high end servers to contain only a
    single CPU.  This is achieved in a number of different
    fashions.</para>
    <section xml:id="symmetric_multi_processing">
      <info>
        <title>Symmetric Multi-Processing</title>
      </info>
      <para>Symmetric Multi-Processing, commonly shortened to
      <emphasis>SMP</emphasis>, is currently the most common
      configuration for including multiple CPUs in a single
      system.</para>
      <para>The symmetric term refers to the fact that all the CPUs in
      the system are the same (e.g. architecture, clock speed).  In a
      SMP system there are multiple processors that share other all
      other system resources (memory, disk, etc).</para>
      <section>
        <info>
          <title>Cache Coherency</title>
        </info>
        <para>For the most part, the CPUs in the system work
      independently; each has its own set of registers, program
      counter, etc.  Despite running separately, there is one
      component that requires strict synchronisation.</para>
        <para>This is the CPU cache; remember the cache is a small
        area of quickly accessible memory that mirrors values stored
        in main system memory.  If one CPU modifies data in main
        memory and another CPU has an old copy of that memory in its
        cache the system will obviously not be in a consistent state.
        Note that the problem only occurs when processors are writing
        to memory, since if a value is only read the data will be
        consistent.</para>
        <para>To co-ordinate keeping the cache coherent on all
	processors an SMP system uses <emphasis>snooping</emphasis>.
	Snooping is where a processor listens on a bus which all
	processors are connected to for cache events, and updates its
	cache accordingly.</para>
        <para>One protocol for doing this is the
	<emphasis>MOESI</emphasis> protocol; standing for Modified,
	Owner, Exclusive, Shared, Invalid.  Each of these is a state
	that a cache line can be in on a processor in the system.
	There are other protocols for doing as much, however they all
	share similar concepts.  Below we examine MOESI so you have an
	idea of what the process entails.</para>
        <para>When a processor requires reading a cache line from main
	memory, it firstly has to snoop all other processors in the
	system to see if they currently know anything about that area
	of memory (e.g. have it cached).  If it does not exist in any
	other process, then the processor can load the memory into
	cache and mark it as <emphasis>exclusive</emphasis>.  When it
	writes to the cache, it then changes state to be
	<emphasis>modified</emphasis>.  Here the specific details of
	the cache come into play; some caches will immediately write
	back the modified cache to system memory (known as a
	<emphasis>write-through</emphasis> cache, because writes go
	through to main memory).  Others will not, and leave the
	modified value only in the cache until it is evicted, when the
	cache becomes full for example.</para>
        <para>The other case is where the processor snoops and finds
	that the value is in another processors cache.  If this value
	has already been marked as <emphasis>modified</emphasis>, it
	will copy the data into its own cache and mark it as
	<emphasis>shared</emphasis>.  It will send a message for the
	other processor (that we got the data from) to mark its cache
	line as <emphasis>owner</emphasis>.  Now imagine that a third
	processor in the system wants to use that memory too.  It will
	snoop and find both a <emphasis>shared</emphasis> and a
	<emphasis>owner</emphasis> copy; it will thus take its value
	from the <emphasis>owner</emphasis> value.  While all the
	other processors are only reading the value, the cache line
	stays <emphasis>shared</emphasis> in the system.  However,
	when one processor needs to update the value it sends an
	<emphasis>invalidate</emphasis> message through the system.
	Any processors with that cache line must then mark it as
	invalid, because it not longer reflects the "true" value.
	When the processor sends the invalidate message, it marks the
	cache line as <emphasis>modified</emphasis> in its cache and
	all others will mark as <emphasis>invalid</emphasis> (note
	that if the cache line is <emphasis>exclusive</emphasis> the
	processor knows that no other processor is depending on it so
	can avoid sending an invalidate message).</para>
        <para>From this point the process starts all over.  Thus
	whichever processor has the <emphasis>modified</emphasis>
	value has the responsibility of writing the true value back to
	RAM when it is evicted from the cache.  By thinking through
	the protocol you can see that this ensures consistency of
	cache lines between processors.</para>
        <para>There are several issues with this system as the number
	of processors starts to increase.  With only a few processors,
	the overhead of checking if another processor has the cache
	line (a read snoop) or invalidating the data in every other
	processor (invalidate snoop) is manageable; but as the number
	of processors increase so does the bus traffic.  This is why
	SMP systems usually only scale up to around 8
	processors.</para>
        <para>Having the processors all on the same bus starts to
	present physical problems as well.  Physical properties of
	wires only allow them to be laid out at certain distances
	from each other and to only have certain lengths.  With
	processors that run at many gigahertz the speed of light
	starts to become a real consideration in how long it takes
	messages to move around a system.</para>
        <para>Note that system software usually has no part in this
	process, although programmers should be aware of what the
	hardware is doing underneath in response to the programs they
	design to maximise performance.</para>
        <section xml:id="cache_exclusivity_in_smp">
          <info>
            <title>Cache exclusivity in SMP systems</title>
          </info>
          <para>In <xref linkend="cache_in_depth"/> we described
	    <emphasis>inclusive</emphasis> v
	    <emphasis>exclusive</emphasis> caches.  In general, L1
	    caches are usually inclusive &#x2014; that is all data in
	    the L1 cache also resides in the L2 cache. In a
	    multiprocessor system, an inclusive L1 cache means that
	    only the L2 cache need snoop memory traffic to maintain
	    coherency, since any changes in L2 will be guaranteed to
	    be reflected by L1. This reduces the complexity of the L1
	    and de-couples it from the snooping process allowing it to
	    be faster.</para>
          <para>Again, in general, most all modern high-end
	    (e.g. not targeted at embedded) processors have a
	    write-through policy for the L1 cache, and a write-back
	    policy for the lower level caches. There are several
	    reasons for this.  Since in this class of processors L2
	    caches are almost exclusively on-chip and generally quite
	    fast the penalties from having L1 write-through are not
	    the major consideration. Further, since L1 sizes are
	    small, pools of written data unlikely to be read in the
	    future could cause pollution of the limited L1 resource.
	    Additionally, a write-through L1 does not have to be
	    concerned if it has outstanding dirty data, hence can pass
	    the extra coherency logic to the L2 (which, as we
	    mentioned, already has a larger part to play in cache
	    coherency).</para>
        </section>
      </section>
      <section>
        <info>
          <title>Hyperthreading</title>
        </info>
        <para>Much of the time of a modern processor is spent waiting
	for much slower devices in the memory hierarchy to deliver
	data for processing.</para>
        <para>Thus strategies to keep the pipeline of the processor
	full are paramount.  One strategy is to include enough
	registers and state logic such that two instruction streams
	can be processed at the same time.  This makes one CPU look
	for all intents and purposes like two CPUs.</para>
        <para>While each CPU has its own registers, they still have to
	share the core logic, cache and input and output bandwidth
	from the CPU to memory.  So while two instruction streams can
	keep the core logic of the processor busier, the performance
	increase will not be as great has having two physically
	separate CPUs.  Typically the performance improvement is below
	20% (XXX check), however it can be drastically better or worse
	depending on the workloads.</para>
      </section>
      <section>
        <info>
          <title>Multi Core</title>
        </info>
        <para>With increased ability to fit more and more transistors
	on a chip, it became possible to put two or more processors in
	the same physical package.  Most common is dual-core, where
	two processor cores are in the same chip.  These cores, unlike
	hyperthreading, are full processors and so appear as two
	physically separate processors a la a SMP system.</para>
        <para>While generally the processors have their own L1 cache,
	they do have to share the bus connecting to main memory and
	other devices.  Thus performance is not as great as a full SMP
	system, but considerably better than a hyperthreading system
	(in fact, each core can still implement hyperthreading for an
	additional enhancement).</para>
        <para>Multi core processors also have some advantages not
	performance related.  As we mentioned, external physical
	buses between processors have physical limits; by containing
	the processors on the same piece of silicon extremely close to
	each other some of these problems can be worked around.  The
	power requirements for multi core processors are much less
	than for two separate processors. This means that there is
	less heat needing to be dissipated which can be a big
	advantage in data centre applications where computers are
	packed together and cooling considerations can be
	considerable.  By having the cores in the same physical
	package it makes muti-processing practical in applications
	where it otherwise would not be, such as laptops.  It is also
	considerably cheaper to only have to produce one chip rather
	than two.</para>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section>
      <info>
        <title>Clusters</title>
      </info>
      <para>Many applications require systems much larger than the
	number of processors a SMP system can scale to.  One way of
	scaling up the system further is a
	<emphasis>cluster</emphasis>.</para>
      <para>A cluster is simply a number of individual computers
	which have some ability to talk to each other.  At the
	hardware level the systems have no knowledge of each other;
	the task of stitching the individual computers together is left
	up to software.</para>
      <para>Software such as MPI allow programmers to write their
	software and then "farm out" parts of the program to other
	computers in the system.  For example, image a loop that
	executes several thousand times performing independent action
	(that is no iteration of the loop affects any other
	iteration).  With four computers in a cluster, the software
	could make each computer do 250 loops each.</para>
      <para>The interconnect between the computers varies, and may
	be as slow as an internet link or as fast as dedicated,
	special buses (Infiniband).  Whatever the interconnect,
	however, it is still going to be further down the memory
	hierarchy and much, much slower than RAM.  Thus a cluster will
	not perform well in a situation when each CPU requires access
	to data that may be stored in the RAM of another computer;
	since each time this happens the software will need to request
	a copy of the data from the other computer, copy across the
	slow link and into local RAM before the processor can get any
	work done.</para>
      <para>However, many applications <emphasis>do not</emphasis>
	require this constant copying around between computers.  One
	large scale example is SETI@Home, where data collected from a
	radio antenna is analysed for signs of Alien life.  Each
	computer can be distributed a few minutes of data to analyse,
	and only needs report back a summary of what it found.
	SETI@Home is effectively a very large, dedicated
	cluster.</para>
      <para>Another application is rendering of images, especially
	for special effects in films.  Each computer can be handed a
	single frame of the movie which contains the wire-frame models,
	textures and light sources which needs to be combined
	(rendered) into the amazing special effects we now take for
	grained.  Since each frame is static, once the computer has
	the initial input it does not need any more communication
	until the final frame is ready to be sent back and combined
	into the move.  For example the block-buster Lord of the Rings
	had their special effects rendered on a huge cluster running
	Linux.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <info>
        <title>Non-Uniform Memory Access</title>
      </info>
      <para>Non-Uniform Memory Access, more commonly abbreviated to
	NUMA, is almost the opposite of a cluster system mentioned
	above.  As in a cluster system it is made up of individual
	nodes linked together, however the linkage between nodes is
	highly specialised (and expensive!).  As opposed to a cluster
	system where the hardware has no knowledge of the linkage
	between nodes, in a NUMA system the
	<emphasis>software</emphasis> has no (well, less) knowledge
	about the layout of the system and the hardware does all the
	work to link the nodes together.</para>
      <para>The term <emphasis>non uniform memory access</emphasis>
      comes from the fact that RAM may not be local to the CPU and so
      data may need to be accessed from a node some distance away.
      This obviously takes longer, and is in contrast to a single
      processor or SMP system where RAM is directly attached and
      always takes a constant (uniform) time to access.</para>
      <section>
        <info>
          <title>NUMA Machine Layout</title>
        </info>
        <para>With so many nodes talking to each other in a system,
      minimising the distance between each node is of paramount
      importance.  Obviously it is best if every single node has a
      direct link to every other node as this minimises the distance
      any one node needs to go to find data.  This is not a practical
      situation when the number of nodes starts growing into the
      hundreds and thousands as it does with large supercomputers; if
      you remember your high school maths the problem is basically a
      combination taken two at a time (each node talking to another),
      and will grow
      <computeroutput>n!/2*(n-2)!</computeroutput>.</para>
        <para>To combat this exponential growth alternative layouts are
      used to trade off the distance between nodes with the
      interconnects required.  One such layout common in modern NUMA
      architectures is the hypercube.</para>
        <para>A hypercube has a strict mathematical definition (way
      beyond this discussion) but as a cube is a 3 dimensional
      counterpart of a square, so a hypercube is a 4 dimensional
      counterpart of a cube.</para>
        <figure>
          <info>
            <title>A Hypercube</title>
          </info>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="chapter02/figures/hypercube.eps" format="EPS"/>
            </imageobject>
            <imageobject role="fo">
              <imagedata fileref="figures/hypercube.svg" format="SVG" scalefit="1" width="100%" contentdepth="100%"/>
            </imageobject>
            <imageobject role="html">
              <imagedata fileref="chapter02/figures/hypercube.png" format="PNG"/>
            </imageobject>
            <caption>
              <para>An example of a hypercube.  Hypercubes provide a
	  good trade off between distance between nodes and number of
	  interconnections required.</para>
            </caption>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>
        <para>Above we can see the outer cube contains four 8 nodes.
      The maximum number of paths required for any node to talk to
      another node is 3.  When another cube is placed inside this
      cube, we now have double the number of processors but the
      maximum path cost has only increased to 4.  This means as the
      number of processors grow by 2<superscript>n</superscript> the
      maximum path cost grows only linearly.</para>
      </section>
      <section>
        <info>
          <title>Cache Coherency</title>
        </info>
        <para>Cache coherency can still be maintained in a NUMA system
      (this is referred to as a cache-coherent NUMA system, or
      ccNUMA).  As we mentioned, the broadcast based scheme used to
      keep the processor caches coherent in an SMP system does not
      scale to hundreds or even thousands of processors in a large
      NUMA system.  One common scheme for cache coherency in a NUMA
      system is referred to as a <emphasis>directory based
      model</emphasis>.  In this model processors in the system
      communicate to special cache directory hardware.  The directory
      hardware maintains a consistent picture to each processor; this
      abstraction hides the working of the NUMA system from the
      processor.</para>
        <para>The Censier and Feautrier directory based scheme
	maintains a central directory where each memory block has a
	flag bit known as the <emphasis>valid bit</emphasis> for each
	processor and a single <emphasis>dirty</emphasis> bit.  When a
	processor reads the memory into its cache, the directory sets
	the valid bit for that processor.</para>
        <para>When a processor wishes to write to the cache line the
	directory needs to set the dirty bit for the memory block.
	This involves sending an invalidate message to those
	processors who are using the cache line (and only those
	processors whose flag are set; avoiding broadcast
	traffic).</para>
        <para>After this should any other processor try to read the
	memory block the directory will find the dirty bit set.  The
	directory will need to get the updated cache line from the
	processor with the valid bit currently set, write the dirty
	data back to main memory and then provide that data back to
	the requesting processor, setting the valid bit for the
	requesting processor in the process.  Note that this is
	transparent to the requesting processor and the directory may
	need to get that data from somewhere very close or somewhere
	very far away.
	</para>
        <para>Obviously having thousands of processors communicating
	to a single directory does also not scale well.  Extensions to
	the scheme involve having a hierarchy of directories that
	communicate between each other using a separate protocol.  The
	directories can use a more general purpose communications
	network to talk between each other, rather than a CPU bus,
	allowing scaling to much larger systems.</para>
      </section>
      <section>
        <info>
          <title>NUMA Applications</title>
        </info>
        <para>NUMA systems are best suited to the types of problems that
      require much interaction between processor and memory.  For
      example, in weather simulations a common idiom is to divide the
      environment up into small "boxes" which respond in different
      ways (oceans and land reflect or store different amounts of
      heat, for example).  As simulations are run, small variations
      will be fed in to see what the overall result is.  As each box
      influences the surrounding boxes (e.g. a bit more sun means a
      particular box puts out more heat, affecting the boxes next to
      it) there will be much communication (contrast that with the
      individual image frames for a rendering process, each of which
      does not influence the other).  A similar process might happen
      if you were modelling a car crash, where each small box of the
      simulated car folds in some way and absorbs some amount of
      energy.</para>
        <para>Although the software has no directly knowledge that the
      underlying system is a NUMA system, programmers need to be
      careful when programming for the system to get maximum
      performance.  Obviously keeping memory close to the processor
      that is going to use it will result in the best performance.
      Programmers need to use techniques such as
      <emphasis>profiling</emphasis> to analyse the code paths taken
      and what consequences their code is causing for the system to
      extract best performance.</para>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section>
      <info>
        <title>Memory ordering, locking and atomic operations</title>
      </info>
      <para>The multi-level cache, superscalar multi-processor
      architecture brings with it some interesting issues relating to
      how a programmer sees the processor running code.</para>
      <para>Imagine program code is running on two processors
      simultaneously, both processors sharing effectively one large
      area of memory.  If one processor issues a store instruction, to
      put a register value into memory, when can it be sure that the
      other processor does a load of that memory it will see the
      correct value?</para>
      <para>In the simplest situation the system could guarantee that
      if a program executes a store instruction, any subsequent load
      instructions will see this value.  This is referred to as
      <emphasis>strict memory ordering</emphasis>, since the rules
      allow no room for movement.  You should be starting to realise
      why this sort of thing is a serious impediment to performance of
      the system.</para>
      <para>Much of the time, the memory ordering is not required to
      be so strict.  The programmer can identify points where they
      need to be sure that all outstanding operations are seen
      globally, but in between these points there may be many
      instructions where the semantics are not important.</para>
      <para>Take, for example, the following situation.</para>
      <example>
        <info>
          <title>Memory Ordering</title>
        </info>
        <programlisting linenumbering="numbered" language="c"><xi:include href="code/memorder.c" parse="text"/></programlisting>
      </example>
      <para>In this example, we have two stores that can be done in
      any particular order, as it suits the processor.  However, in
      the final case, the pointer must only be updated once the two
      previous stores are known to have been done.  Otherwise another
      processor might look at the value of
      <computeroutput>p</computeroutput>, follow the pointer to the
      memory, load it, and get some completely incorrect value!</para>
      <para>To indicate this, loads and stores have to have
      <emphasis>semantics</emphasis> that describe what behaviour they
      must have.  Memory semantics are described in terms of
      <emphasis>fences</emphasis> that dictate how loads and stores
      may be reordered around the load or store.</para>
      <para>By default, a load or store can be re-ordered
      anywhere.</para>
      <para><emphasis>Acquire</emphasis> semantics is like a fence
      that only allows load and stores to move downwards through it.
      That is, when this load or store is complete you can be
      guaranteed that any later load or stores will see the value
      (since they can not be moved above it).</para>
      <para><emphasis>Release</emphasis> semantics is the opposite,
      that is a fence that allows any load or stores to be done before
      it (move upwards), but nothing before it to move downwards past
      it.  Thus, when load or store with release semantics is
      processed, you can be store that any earlier load or stores will
      have been complete.</para>
      <figure>
        <info>
          <title>Acquire and Release semantics</title>
        </info>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="chapter02/figures/memorder.eps" format="EPS"/>
          </imageobject>
          <imageobject role="fo">
            <imagedata fileref="figures/memorder.svg" format="SVG" scalefit="1" width="100%" contentdepth="100%"/>
          </imageobject>
          <imageobject role="html">
            <imagedata fileref="chapter02/figures/memorder.png" format="PNG"/>
          </imageobject>
          <caption>
            <para>An illustration of valid reorderings around
	  operations with acquire and release semantics.</para>
          </caption>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
      <para>A <emphasis>full memory fence</emphasis> is a combination
      of both; where no loads or stores can be reordered in any
      direction around the current load or store.</para>
      <para>The strictest memory model would use a full memory fence
      for every operation.  The weakest model would leave every load
      and store as a normal re-orderable instruction.</para>
      <section>
        <info>
          <title>Processors and memory models</title>
        </info>
        <para>Different processors implement different memory
	models.</para>
        <para> The x86 (and AMD64) processor has a quite strict memory
	model; all stores have release semantics (that is, the result
	of a store is guaranteed to be seen by any later load or
	store) but all loads have normal semantics.  lock prefix gives
	memory fence.</para>
        <para>Itanium allows all load and stores to be normal, unless
	explicitly told. XXX</para>
      </section>
      <section>
        <info>
          <title>Locking</title>
        </info>
        <para>Knowing the memory ordering requirements of each
        architecture is not practical for all programmers, and would
        make programs difficult to port and debug across different
        processor types.</para>
        <para>Programmers use a higher level of abstraction called
	<emphasis>locking</emphasis> to allow simultaneous
	operation of programs when there are multiple CPUs.</para>
        <para>When a program acquires a lock over a piece of code, no
	other processor can obtain the lock until it is released.
	Before any critical pieces of code, the processor must attempt
	to take the lock; if it can not have it, it does not
	continue.</para>
        <para>You can see how this is tied into the naming of the
	memory ordering semantics in the previous section.  We want to
	ensure that before we <emphasis>acquire</emphasis> a lock, no
	operations that should be protected by the lock are re-ordered
	before it.  This is how acquire semantics works.</para>
        <para>Conversely, when we <emphasis>release</emphasis> the
	lock, we must be sure that every operation we have done whilst
	we held the lock is complete (remember the example of updating
	the pointer previously?).  This is release semantics.</para>
        <para>There are many software libraries available that allow
	programmers to not have to worry about the details of memory
	semantics and simply use the higher level of abstraction of
	<computeroutput>lock()</computeroutput> and
	<computeroutput>unlock()</computeroutput>.</para>
        <section>
          <info>
            <title>Locking difficulties</title>
          </info>
          <para>Locking schemes make programming more complicated, as
	  it is possible to <emphasis>deadlock</emphasis> programs.
	  Imagine if one processor is currently holding a lock over
	  some data, and is currently waiting for a lock for some
	  other piece of data.  If that other processor is waiting for
	  the lock the first processor holds before unlocking the
	  second lock, we have a deadlock situation.  Each processor
	  is waiting for the other and neither can continue without
	  the others lock.</para>
          <para>Often this situation arises because of a subtle
	  <emphasis>race condition</emphasis>; one of the hardest bugs
	  to track down.  If two processors are relying on operations
	  happening in a specific order in time, there is always the
	  possibility of a race condition occurring.  A gamma ray from
	  an exploding star in a different galaxy might hit one of the
	  processors, making it skip a beat, throwing the ordering of
	  operations out.  What will often happen is a deadlock
	  situation like above.  It is for this reason that program
	  ordering needs to be ensured by semantics, and not by
	  relying on one time specific behaviours. (XXX not sure how i
	  can better word that).</para>
          <para>A similar situation is the opposite of deadlock,
	  called <emphasis>livelock</emphasis>.  One strategy to avoid
	  deadlock might be to have a "polite" lock; one that you give
	  up to anyone who asks.  This politeness might cause two
	  threads to be constantly giving each other the lock, without
	  either ever taking the lock long enough to get the critical
	  work done and be finished with the lock (a similar situation
	  in real life might be two people who meet at a door at the
	  same time, both saying "no, you first, I insist".  Neither
	  ends up going through the door!).
	  </para>
        </section>
        <section>
          <info>
            <title>Locking strategies</title>
          </info>
          <para>Underneath, there are many different strategies for
	  implementing the behaviour of locks.</para>
          <para>A simple lock that simply has two states - locked or
	  unlocked, is referred to as a <emphasis>mutex</emphasis>
	  (short for mutual exclusion; that is if one person has it
	  the other can not have it).</para>
          <para>There are, however, a number of ways to implement a
	  mutex lock.  In the simplest case, we have what its commonly
	  called a <emphasis>spinlock</emphasis>.  With this type of
	  lock, the processor sits in a tight loop waiting to take the
	  lock; equivalent to it saying "can I have it now" constantly
	  much as a young child might ask of a parent.</para>
          <para>The problem with this strategy is that it essentially
	  wastes time.  Whilst the processor is sitting constantly
	  asking for the lock, it is not doing any useful work.  For
	  locks that are likely to be only held locked for a very
	  short amount of time this may be appropriate, but in many
	  cases the amount of time the lock is held might be
	  considerably longer.</para>
          <para>Thus another strategy is to <emphasis>sleep</emphasis>
	  on a lock.  In this case, if the processor can not have the
	  lock it will start doing some other work, waiting for
	  notification that the lock is available for use (we see in
	  future chapters how the operating system can switch
	  processes and give the processor more work to do).</para>
          <para>A mutex is however just a special case of a
	  <emphasis>semaphore</emphasis>, famously invented by the
	  Dutch computer scientist Dijkstra.  In a case where there
	  are multiple resources available, a semaphore can be set to
	  count accesses to the resources.  In the case where the
	  number of resources is one, you have a mutex.  The operation
	  of semaphores can be detailed in any algorithms book.</para>
          <para>These locking schemes still have some problems
	  however.  In many cases, most people only want to read data
	  which is updated only rarely.  Having all the processors
	  wanting to only read data require taking a lock can lead to
	  <emphasis>lock contention</emphasis> where less work gets
	  done because everyone is waiting to obtain the same lock for
	  some data.  </para>
        </section>
      </section>
      <section>
        <info>
          <title>Atomic Operations</title>
        </info>
        <para>Explain what it is.</para>
      </section>
    </section>
  </section>
</chapter>
