<?xml version="1.0"?>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" version="5.0" xml:id="chapter00">
  <info>
    <title>General Unix and Advanced C</title>
  </info>
  <section xml:id="everything_is_a_file">
    <info>
      <title>
        <emphasis>Everything is a file!</emphasis>
      </title>
    </info>
    <para>An often-quoted tenet of UNIX-like systems such as Linux or
    BSD is <emphasis>everything is a file</emphasis>.</para>
    <para>Imagine a file in the context of something familiar like a
    word processor.  There are two fundamental operations we could use
    on this imaginary word processing file:</para>
    <orderedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Read it (existing saved data from the word processor).</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Write to it (new data from the user).</para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
    <para>Consider some of the common things attached to a computer
    and how they relate to our fundamental file operations:</para>
    <orderedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>The screen</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>The keyboard</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>A printer</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>A CD-ROM</para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
    <para>The screen and printer are both like a write-only file, but
    instead of being stored as bits on a disk the information is
    displayed as dots on a screen or lines on a page. The keyboard is
    like a read only file, with the data coming from keystrokes
    provided by the user.  The CD-ROM is similar, but rather than
    randomly coming from the user the data is stored directly on the
    disk.</para>
    <para>Thus the concept of a file is a good
    <emphasis>abstraction</emphasis> of either a sink for, or source
    of, data.  As such it is an excellent abstraction of all the
    devices one might attach to the computer.  This realisation is the
    great power of UNIX and is evident across the design of the entire
    platform.  It is one of the fundamental roles of the operating
    system to provide this abstraction of the hardware to the
    programmer.</para>
    <para>It is probably not too much of a stretch to say abstraction
    is <emphasis>the</emphasis> primary concept that underpins all
    modern computing.  No one person can understand everything from
    designing a modern user-interface to the internal workings of a
    modern CPU, much less build it all themselves.  To programmers,
    abstractions are the common language that allows us to collaborate
    and invent.</para>
    <para>Learning to navigate across abstractions gives one greater
      insight into how to <emphasis>use</emphasis> the abstractions in
      the best and most innovative ways.  In this book, we are
      concerned with abstractions at the lowest layers; between
      applications and the operating system and the operating system
      and hardware.  Above this lies many more layers, each worthy of
      their own books.  As these chapters progress, you will hopefully
      gain some insight into the abstractions presented by a modern
      operating system.</para>
    <figure>
      <info>
        <title>Abstraction</title>
      </info>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="chapter00/figures/abstraction.eps" format="EPS"/>
        </imageobject>
        <imageobject role="fo">
          <imagedata fileref="figures/abstraction.svg" format="SVG" scalefit="1" width="100%" contentdepth="100%"/>
        </imageobject>
        <imageobject role="html">
          <imagedata fileref="chapter00/figures/abstraction.png" format="PNG"/>
        </imageobject>
        <textobject>
          <phrase>Can you spot the difference between a CD-ROM and a keyboard?  As an application programmer, you should not be able to.</phrase>
        </textobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="abstration">
    <info>
      <title>Implementing abstraction</title>
    </info>
    <para>In general, abstraction is implemented by what is
    generically termed an <emphasis>Application Programming
    Interface</emphasis> (API).  API is a somewhat nebulous term that
    means different things in the context of various programming
    endeavours.  Fundamentally, a programmer designs a set of
    functions and documents their interface and functionality with the
    principle that the actual implementation providing the API is
    opaque.</para>
    <para>For example, many large web applications provide an API
    accessible via HTTP.  Accessing data via this method surely
    triggers many complicated series of remote procedure calls,
    database queries and data transfers, all of which are opaque to
    the end user who simply receives the contracted data.</para>
    <para>Those familiar with <emphasis>object-oriented</emphasis>
      languages such as Java, Python or C++ would be familiar with the
      abstraction provided by <emphasis>classes</emphasis>.  Methods
      provide the interface to the class, but abstract the
      implementation.</para>
    <section>
      <info>
        <title>Implementing abstraction with C</title>
      </info>
      <para>A common method used in the Linux kernel and other large C
      code bases, which lack a built-in concept of object-orientation,
      is <emphasis>function pointers</emphasis>.  Learning to read
      this idiom is key to navigating most large C code bases.  By
      understanding how to read the abstractions provided within the
      code an understanding of internal API designs can be
      built.</para>
      <example xml:id="abstraction-code">
        <info>
          <title>Abstraction with function pointers</title>
        </info>
        <programlisting language="c">
          <xi:include href="code/abstraction.c" parse="text"/>
        </programlisting>
      </example>
      <para>Code such as the above is the simplest example of
      constructs used repeatedly throughout the Linux Kernel and other
      C programs.  Let's have a look at some specific elements.</para>
      <para>We start out with a structure that defines the API
      (<computeroutput>struct greet_api</computeroutput>).  The
      functions whose names are encased in parentheses with a pointer
      marker describe a <emphasis>function
      pointer</emphasis><footnote><para>Often you will see that the
      names of the parameters are omitted, and only the type of the
      parameter is specified.  This allows the implementer to specify
      their own parameter names avoiding warnings from the
      compiler.</para></footnote>.  The function pointer describes the
      <emphasis>prototype</emphasis> of the function it must point to;
      pointing it at a function without the correct return type or
      parameters will generate a compiler warning at least; if left in
      code will likely lead to incorrect operation or crashes.</para>

      <para>We then have our implementation of the API.  Often for
      more complex functionality you will see an idiom where API
      implementation functions will only be a wrapper around other
      functions that are conventionally prepended with one or or two
      underscores<footnote><para>A double-underscore function
      <computeroutput>__foo</computeroutput> may conversationally be
      referred to as "dunder foo".</para></footnote>
      (i.e. <computeroutput>say_hello_fn()</computeroutput> would call
      another function
      <computeroutput>_say_hello_function()</computeroutput>).  This
      has several uses; generally it relates to having simpler and
      smaller parts of the API (marshalling or checking arguments, for
      example) separate from more complex implementation, which often
      eases the path to significant changes in the internal workings
      whilst ensuring the API remains constant.  Our implementation is
      very simple, however, and doesn't even need it's own support
      functions.  In various projects, single-, double- or even
      triple-underscore function prefixes will mean different things,
      but universally it is a visual warning that the function is not
      supposed to be called directly from "beyond" the API.</para>
      <para>Second to last, we fill out the function pointers in
      <computeroutput>struct greet_api greet_api</computeroutput>.
      The name of the function is a pointer; therefore there is no
      need to take the address of the function
      (i.e. <computeroutput>&amp;say_hello_fn</computeroutput>).</para>
      <para>Finally we can call the API functions through the
    structure in <computeroutput>main</computeroutput>.</para>
      <para>You will see this idiom constantly when navigating the
        source code.  The tiny example below is taken from
        <computeroutput>include/linux/virtio.h</computeroutput> in the
        Linux kernel source to illustrate:</para>
      <example xml:id="virtio-abstraction">
        <info>
          <title>Abstraction in
	<computeroutput>include/linux/virtio.h</computeroutput></title>
        </info>
        <programlisting language="c">
          <xi:include href="code/virtio.h" parse="text"/>
        </programlisting>
      </example>
      <para> It's only necessary to vaguely understand that this
      structure is a description of a virtual I/O device.  We can see
      the user of this API (the device driver author) is expected to
      provide a number of functions that will be called under various
      conditions during system operation (when probing for new
      hardware, when hardware is removed, etc.).  It also contains a
      range of data; structures which should be filled with relevant
      data.</para>
      <para>Starting with descriptors like this is usually the easiest
      way to begin understanding the various layers of kernel
      code.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <info>
        <title>Libraries</title>
      </info>
      <para>Libraries have two roles which illustrate
	abstraction.</para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Allow programmers to reuse commonly accessed code.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Act as a <emphasis>black box</emphasis> implementing
	    functionality for the programmer.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <para>For example, a library implementing access to the raw data
      in JPEG files has both the advantage that the many programs that
      wish to access image files can all use the same library and the
      programmers building these programs do not need to worry about
      the exact details of the JPEG file format, but can concentrate
      their efforts on what their program wants to do with the
      image.</para>
      <para>The standard library of a UNIX platform is generically
        referred to as <computeroutput>libc</computeroutput>.  It
        provides the basic interface to the system: fundamental calls
        such as <computeroutput>read()</computeroutput>,
        <computeroutput>write()</computeroutput> and
        <computeroutput>printf()</computeroutput>.  This API is
        described in its entirety by a specification called
        <computeroutput>POSIX</computeroutput>.  It is freely
        available online and describes the many calls that make up the
        standard UNIX API.</para>

        <para>Most UNIX platforms broadly follow the POSIX standard,
        though often differ in small but sometimes important ways
        (hence the complexity of the various GNU autotools, which
        often try to abstract away these differences for you).  Linux
        has many interfaces that are not specified by POSIX; writing
        applications that use them exclusively will make your
        application less portable.</para>

        <para>Libraries are a fundamental abstraction with many
        details.  Later chapters will describe how libraries work in
        much greater detail.</para>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="file_descriptors">
    <info>
      <title>File Descriptors</title>
    </info>
    <para>One of the first things a UNIX programmer learns is that
    every running program starts with three files already
    opened:</para>
    <table>
      <info>
        <title>Standard Files Provided by Unix</title>
      </info>
      <tgroup cols="4">
        <thead>
          <row>
            <entry>Descriptive Name</entry>
            <entry>Short Name</entry>
            <entry>File Number</entry>
            <entry>Description</entry>
          </row>
        </thead>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry>Standard In</entry>
            <entry>stdin</entry>
            <entry>0</entry>
            <entry>Input from the keyboard</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>Standard Out</entry>
            <entry>stdout</entry>
            <entry>1</entry>
            <entry>Output to the console</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>Standard Error</entry>
            <entry>stderr</entry>
            <entry>2</entry>
            <entry>Error output to the console</entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>
    <figure>
      <info>
        <title>Default Unix Files</title>
      </info>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="chapter00/figures/stdfds.eps" format="EPS"/>
        </imageobject>
        <imageobject role="fo">
          <imagedata fileref="figures/stdfds.svg" format="SVG" scalefit="1" width="100%" contentdepth="100%"/>
        </imageobject>
        <imageobject role="html">
          <imagedata fileref="chapter00/figures/stdfds.png" format="PNG"/>
        </imageobject>
        <textobject>
          <phrase>The standard files opened with any UNIX program.</phrase>
        </textobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>
    <para>This raises the question what an <emphasis>open
        file</emphasis> represents.  The value returned by an
        <computeroutput>open</computeroutput> call is termed a
        <emphasis>file descriptor</emphasis> and is essentially an
        index into an array of open files kept by the kernel.</para>
    <figure xml:id="fd_abstraction">
      <info>
        <title>Abstraction</title>
      </info>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="chapter00/figures/file-descriptors.eps" format="EPS"/>
        </imageobject>
        <imageobject role="fo">
          <imagedata fileref="figures/file-descriptors.svg" format="SVG" scalefit="1" width="100%" contentdepth="100%"/>
        </imageobject>
        <imageobject role="html">
          <imagedata fileref="chapter00/figures/file-descriptors.png" format="PNG"/>
        </imageobject>
        <textobject>
          <phrase>File descriptors associate the abstraction provided
          by device drivers with a file interface provided to a
          user.</phrase>
        </textobject>
      </mediaobject>
      <caption>
        <para>File descriptors are an index into a file descriptor
        table stored by the kernel.  The kernel creates a file
        descriptor in response to an
        <computeroutput>open</computeroutput> call and associates the
        file descriptor with some abstraction of an underlying
        file-like object, be that an actual hardware device, or a
        file system or something else entirely.  Consequently a
        process's <computeroutput>read</computeroutput> or
        <computeroutput>write</computeroutput> calls that reference
        that file descriptor are routed to the correct place by the
        kernel to ultimately do something useful.</para>
      </caption>
    </figure>
    <para>In short, the file descriptor is the gateway into the
    kernel's abstractions of underlying hardware.  An overall view of
    the abstraction for physical-devices is shown in <xref
    linkend="fd_abstraction"/>.</para>
    <para>Starting at the lowest level, the operating system requires
    a programmer to create a <emphasis>device driver</emphasis> to be
    able to communicate with a hardware device.  This device driver is
    written to an API provided by the kernel just like in <xref
    linkend="virtio-abstraction"/>; the device driver will provide a
    range of functions which are called by the kernel in response to
    various requirements.  In the simplified example above, we can see
    the drivers provide a <computeroutput>read</computeroutput> and
    <computeroutput>write</computeroutput> function that will be
    called in response to the analogous operations on the
    file descriptor. The device driver knows how to convert these
    generic requests into specific requests or commands for a
    particular device.</para>
    <para>To provide the abstraction to user-space, the kernel
    provides a file-interface via what is generically termed a
    <emphasis>device layer</emphasis>.  Physical devices on the host
    are represented by a file in a special file system such as
    <computeroutput>/dev</computeroutput>.  In UNIX-like systems,
    so-called <emphasis>device-nodes</emphasis> have what are termed a
    <emphasis>major</emphasis> and a <emphasis>minor</emphasis>
    number, which allow the kernel to associate particular nodes with
    their underlying driver.  These can be identified via
    <computeroutput>ls</computeroutput> as illustrated in <xref
    linkend="major-minor-numbers"/>.</para>
    <example xml:id="major-minor-numbers">
      <info>
        <title>Example of major and minor numbers</title>
      </info>
      <programlisting>
        <xi:include href="code/major-minor.txt" parse="text"/>
      </programlisting>
    </example>
    <para>This brings us to the file descriptor, which is the handle
    user-space uses to talk to the underlying device.  In a broad
    sense, what happens when a file is
    <computeroutput>open</computeroutput>ed is that the kernel is
    using the path information to map the file descriptor with
    something that provides an appropriate
    <computeroutput>read</computeroutput> and
    <computeroutput>write</computeroutput>, etc., API.  When this
    <computeroutput>open</computeroutput> is for a device
    (<computeroutput>/dev/sr0</computeroutput> above), the major and
    minor number of the opened device node provides the information
    the kernel needs to find the correct device driver and complete
    the mapping.  The kernel will then know how to route further calls
    such as <computeroutput>read</computeroutput> to the underlying
    functions provided by the device driver.</para>
    <para>A non-device file operates similarly, although there are
    more layers in between.  The abstraction here is the
    <emphasis>mount point</emphasis>; mounting a file system has the
    dual purpose of setting up a mapping so the file system knows the
    underlying device that provides the storage and the kernel knows
    that files opened under that mount-point should be directed to the
    file system driver.  Like device drivers, file systems are written
    to a particular generic file system API provided by the kernel.
    </para>
    <para>There are indeed many other layers that complicate the
    picture in real-life.  For example, the kernel will go to great
    efforts to cache as much data from disks as possible in
    otherwise-free memory; this provides many speed advantages.  It
    will also try to organise device access in the most efficient ways
    possible; for example trying to order disk-access to ensure data
    stored physically close together is retrieved together, even if
    the requests did not arrive in sequential order.  Further, many
    devices are of a more generic class such as USB or SCSI devices
    which provide their own abstraction layers to write to.  Thus,
    rather than writing directly to devices, file systems will go
    through these many layers.  Understanding the kernel is to
    understand how these many APIs interrelate and coexist.</para>
    <section>
      <info>
        <title>The Shell</title>
      </info>
      <para>The shell is the gateway to interacting with the operating
        system.  Be it <computeroutput>bash</computeroutput>,
        <computeroutput>zsh</computeroutput>,
        <computeroutput>csh</computeroutput> or any of the many other
        shells, they all fundamentally have only one major task &#x2014; to
        allow you to execute programs (you will begin to understand
        how the shell actually does this when we talk about some of
        the internals of the operating system later).</para>
      <para>But shells do much more than allow you to simply execute a
      program.  They have powerful abilities to redirect files, allow
      you to execute multiple programs simultaneously and script
      complete programs.  These all come back to the
      <emphasis>everything is a file</emphasis> idiom.</para>
      <section>
        <info>
          <title>Redirection</title>
        </info>
        <para>Often we do not want the standard file descriptors
        mentioned in <xref linkend="file_descriptors"/> to point to
        their default places.  For example, you may wish to capture
        all the output of a program into a file on disk or,
        alternatively, have it read its commands from a file you
        prepared earlier.  Another useful task might like to pass the
        output of one program to the input of another.  With the
        operating system, the shell facilitates all this and
        more.</para>
        <table>
          <info>
            <title>Standard Shell Redirection Facilities</title>
          </info>
          <tgroup cols="4">
            <thead>
              <row>
                <entry>Name</entry>
                <entry>Command</entry>
                <entry>Description</entry>
                <entry>Example</entry>
              </row>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
              <row>
                <entry>Redirect to a file</entry>
                <entry>
                  <computeroutput>&gt; filename</computeroutput>
                </entry>
                <entry>Take all output from standard out and place it into
	    <computeroutput>filename</computeroutput>.  Note using
	    <computeroutput>&gt;&gt;</computeroutput> will append to
	    the file, rather than overwrite it.</entry>
                <entry>
                  <computeroutput>ls &gt; filename</computeroutput>
                </entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>Read from a file</entry>
                <entry>&lt; <computeroutput>filename</computeroutput></entry>
                <entry>Copy all data from the file to the standard input of the program</entry>
                <entry>
                  <computeroutput>echo &lt; filename</computeroutput>
                </entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>Pipe</entry>
                <entry>
                  <computeroutput>program1 | program2</computeroutput>
                </entry>
                <entry>Take everything from standard out of
	    <computeroutput>program1</computeroutput> and pass it to
	    standard input of
	    <computeroutput>program2</computeroutput></entry>
                <entry>
                  <computeroutput>ls | more</computeroutput>
                </entry>
              </row>
            </tbody>
          </tgroup>
        </table>
      </section>
      <section>
        <info>
          <title>Implementing
        <computeroutput>pipe</computeroutput></title>
        </info>
        <para>The implementation of <computeroutput>ls |
        more</computeroutput> is just another example of the power of
        abstraction.  What fundamentally happens here is that instead
        of associating the file descriptor for the standard-output
        with some sort of underlying device (such as the console, for
        output to the terminal), the descriptor is pointed to an
        in-memory buffer provided by the kernel commonly termed a
        <computeroutput>pipe</computeroutput>.  The trick here is that
        another process can associate its standard
        <emphasis>input</emphasis> with the other side of this same
        buffer and effectively consume the output of the other
        process.  This is illustrated in <xref
        linkend="process_pipe"/>.</para>
        <figure xml:id="process_pipe">
          <info>
            <title>A pipe in action</title>
          </info>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="chapter00/figures/pipe.eps" format="EPS"/>
            </imageobject>
            <imageobject role="fo">
              <imagedata fileref="figures/pipe.svg" format="SVG" scalefit="1" width="100%" contentdepth="100%"/>
            </imageobject>
            <imageobject role="html">
              <imagedata fileref="chapter00/figures/pipe.png" format="PNG"/>
            </imageobject>
            <textobject>
              <phrase>The pipe is an in-memory buffer provided by the
	  kernel which allows the output of one process to be consumed
	  as the input to another.</phrase>
            </textobject>
          </mediaobject>
          <caption>
            <para>The pipe is an in-memory buffer that connects two
            processes together.  file descriptors point to the pipe
            object, which buffers data sent to it (via a
            <computeroutput>write</computeroutput>) to be
            <emphasis>drained</emphasis> (via a
            <computeroutput>read</computeroutput>).</para>
          </caption>
        </figure>
        <para>Writes to the pipe are stored by the kernel until a
        corresponding read from the other side
        <emphasis>drains</emphasis> the buffer.  This is a very
        powerful concept and is one of the fundamental forms of
        <emphasis>inter-process communication</emphasis> or IPC in
        UNIX-like operating systems.  The pipe allows more than just a
        data transfer; it can act as a signaling channel.  If a
        process <computeroutput>read</computeroutput>s an empty pipe,
        it will by default <emphasis>block</emphasis> or be put into
        hibernation until there is some data available (this is
        discussed in much greater depth in <xref
        linkend="chapter04"/>).  Thus two processes may use a pipe to
        communicate that some action has been taken just by writing a
        byte of data; rather than the actual data being important, the
        mere presence of <emphasis>any</emphasis> data in the pipe can
        signal a message.  Say for example one process requests that
        another print a file &#x2014; something that will take some
        time.  The two processes may set up a pipe between themselves
        where the requesting process does a
        <computeroutput>read</computeroutput> on the empty pipe; being
        empty, that call blocks and the process does not continue.
        Once the print is done, the other process can write a message
        into the pipe, which effectively wakes up the requesting
        process and signals the work is done.</para>
        <para>Allowing processes to pass data between each other like
        this springs another common UNIX idiom of small tools doing
        one particular thing.  Chaining these small tools gives
        flexibility that a single monolithic tool often can
        not.</para>
      </section>
    </section>
  </section>
</chapter>
