<?xml version="1.0"?>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" version="5.0" xml:id="chapter08">
  <info>
    <title>Dynamic Linking</title>
  </info>
  <section xml:id="code_sharing">
    <info>
      <title>Code Sharing</title>
    </info>
    <para>We know that for the operating system code is considered
      read only, and separate from data.  It seems logical then that
      if programs can not modify code and have large amounts of common
      code, instead of replicating it for every executable it should
      be shared between many executables.</para>
    <para>With virtual memory this can be easily done.  The physical
      pages of memory the library code is loaded into can be easily
      referenced by any number of virtual pages in any number of
      address spaces.  So while you only have one physical copy of the
      library code in system memory, every process can have access to
      that library code at any virtual address it likes.</para>
    <para>Thus people quickly came up with the idea of a
      <emphasis>shared library</emphasis> which, as the name suggests,
      is shared by multiple executables.  Each executable contains a
      reference essentially saying "I need library foo".  When the
      program is loaded, it is up to the system to either check if
      some other program has already loaded the code for library foo
      into memory, and thus share it by mapping pages into the
      executable for that physical memory, or otherwise load the
      library into memory for the executable.</para>
    <para>This process is called <emphasis>dynamic linking</emphasis>
    because it does part of the linking process "on the fly" as
    programs are executed in the system.</para>
    <section>
      <info>
        <title>Dynamic Library Details</title>
      </info>
      <para>Libraries are very much like a program that never gets
      started.  They have code and data sections (functions and
      variables) just like every executable; but no where to start
      running.  They just provide a library of functions for
      developers to call.</para>
      <para>Thus ELF can represent a dynamic library just as it does
      an executable.  There are some fundamental differences, such as
      there is no pointer to where execution should start, but all
      shared libraries are just ELF objects like any other
      executable.</para>
      <para>The ELF header has two mutually exclusive flags,
      <computeroutput>ET_EXEC</computeroutput> and
      <computeroutput>ET_DYN</computeroutput> to mark an ELF file as
      either an executable or a shared object file.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <info>
        <title>Including libraries in an executable</title>
      </info>
      <section>
        <info>
          <title>Compilation</title>
        </info>
        <para>When you compile your program that uses a dynamic
	library, object files are left with references to the library
	functions just as for any other external reference.</para>
        <para>You need to include the <emphasis>header</emphasis> for
	the library so that the compiler knows the specific types of
	the functions you are calling.  Note the compiler only needs
	to know the types associated with a function (such as, it
	takes an <computeroutput>int</computeroutput> and returns a
	<computeroutput>char *</computeroutput>) so that it can
	correctly allocate space for the function call.<footnote><para>This has not always been the case with the C standard.
	Previously, compilers would assume that any function it did
	not know about returned an
	<computeroutput>int</computeroutput>.  On a 32 bit system, the
	size of a pointer is the same size as an
	<computeroutput>int</computeroutput>, so there was no problem.
	However, with a 64 bit system, the size of a pointer is
	generally twice the size of an
	<computeroutput>int</computeroutput> so if the function
	actually returns a pointer, its value will be destroyed.  This
	is clearly not acceptable, as the pointer will thus not point
	to valid memory.  The C99 standard has changed such that you
	are required to specify the types of included
	functions.</para></footnote></para>
      </section>
      <section>
        <info>
          <title>Linking</title>
        </info>
        <para>Even though the <emphasis>dynamic linker</emphasis> does
	a lot of the work for shared libraries, the traditional linker
	still has a role to play in creating the executable.</para>
        <para>The traditional linker needs to leave a pointer in the
	executable so that the dynamic linker knows what library will
	satisfy the dependencies at runtime.</para>
        <para>The <computeroutput>dynamic</computeroutput> section of
	the executable requires a
	<computeroutput>NEEDED</computeroutput> entry for each shared
	library that the executable depends on.</para>
        <para>Again, we can inspect these fields with the
	<computeroutput>readelf</computeroutput> program.  Below we
	have a look at a very standard binary,
	<computeroutput>/bin/ls</computeroutput></para>
        <example>
          <info>
            <title>Specifying Dynamic Libraries</title>
          </info>
          <programlisting linenumbering="numbered"><xi:include href="code/dynamic-needed.txt" parse="text"/></programlisting>
        </example>
        <para>You can see that it specifies three libraries.  The most
	common library shared by most, if not all, programs on the
	system is <computeroutput>libc</computeroutput>.  There are
	also some other libraries that the program needs to run
	correctly.</para>
        <para>Reading the ELF file directly is sometimes useful, but
	the usual way to inspect a dynamically linked executable is
	via <computeroutput>ldd</computeroutput>.
	<computeroutput>ldd</computeroutput> "walks" the dependencies
	of libraries for you; that is if a library depends on another
	library, it will show it to you.</para>
        <example>
          <info>
            <title>Looking at dynamic libraries</title>
          </info>
          <programlisting linenumbering="numbered"><xi:include href="code/ldd.txt" parse="text"/></programlisting>
        </example>
        <para>We can see above that
	<computeroutput>libpthread</computeroutput> has been required
	from somewhere.  If we do a little digging, we can see that
	the requirement comes from
	<computeroutput>librt</computeroutput>.</para>
      </section>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="dynamic_linker">
    <info>
      <title>The Dynamic Linker</title>
    </info>
    <para>The dynamic linker is the program that manages shared
    dynamic libraries on behalf of an executable.  It works to load
    libraries into memory and modify the program at runtime to call
    the functions in the library.</para>
    <para>ELF allows executables to specify an
    <emphasis>interpreter</emphasis>, which is a program that should
    be used to run the executable.  The compiler and static linker set
    the interpreter of executables that rely on dynamic libraries to
    be the dynamic linker.</para>
    <example>
      <info>
        <title>Checking the program interpreter</title>
      </info>
      <programlisting linenumbering="numbered"><xi:include href="code/interpreter.txt" parse="text"/></programlisting>
    </example>
    <para>You can see above that the interpreter is set to be
    <application>/lib/ld-linux-ia64.so.2</application>, which is the
    dynamic linker.  When the kernel loads the binary for execution,
    it will check if the <computeroutput>PT_INTERP</computeroutput>
    field is present, and if so load what it points to into memory and
    start it.</para>
    <para>We mentioned that dynamically linked executables leave
    behind references that need to be fixed with information that
    isn't available until runtime, such as the address of a function
    in a shared library.  The references that are left behind are
    called <emphasis>relocations</emphasis>.</para>
    <section xml:id="dynamic_relocations">
      <info>
        <title>Relocations</title>
      </info>
      <para>The essential part of the dynamic linker is fixing up
      addresses at runtime, which is the only time you can know for
      certain where you are loaded in memory.  A relocation can simply
      be thought of as a note that a particular address will need to
      be fixed at load time.  Before the code is ready to run you will
      need to go through and read all the relocations and fix the
      addresses it refers to to point to the right place.</para>
      <table>
        <info>
          <title>Relocation Example</title>
        </info>
        <tgroup cols="2">
          <thead>
            <row>
              <entry>Address</entry>
              <entry>Action</entry>
            </row>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>0x123456</entry>
              <entry>Address of symbol "x"</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>0x564773</entry>
              <entry>Function X</entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </table>
      <para>There are many types of relocation for each architecture,
      and each types exact behaviour is documented as part of the ABI
      for the system.  The definition of a relocation is quite
      straight forward.</para>
      <example>
        <info>
          <title>Relocation as defined by ELF</title>
        </info>
        <programlisting linenumbering="numbered"><xi:include href="code/elfrelocs.txt" parse="text"/></programlisting>
      </example>
      <para>The <computeroutput>r_offset</computeroutput> field refers
      to the offset in the file that needs to be fixed up.  The
      <computeroutput>r_info</computeroutput> field specifies the type
      of relocation which describes what exactly must be done to fix
      this code up.  The simplest relocation usually defined for an
      architecture is simply the value of the symbol.  In this case
      you simply substitute the address of the symbol at the location
      specified, and the relocation has been "fixed-up".</para>
      <para>The two types, one with an addend and one without specify
      different ways for the relocation to operate.  An addend is
      simply something that should be added to the fixed up address to
      find the correct address.  For example, if the relocation is for
      the symbol <computeroutput>i</computeroutput> because the
      original code is doing something like
      <computeroutput>i[8]</computeroutput> the addend will be set to
      8.  This means "find the address of
      <computeroutput>i</computeroutput>, and go 8 past it".</para>
      <para>That addend value needs to be stored somewhere.  The two
      solutions are covered by the two forms.  In the
      <computeroutput>REL</computeroutput> form the addend is actually
      store in the program code in the place where the fixed up
      address should be.  This means that to fix up the address
      properly, you need to first read the memory you are about to fix
      up to get any addend, store that, find the "real" address, add
      the addend to it and then write it back (over the addend).  The
      <computeroutput>RELA</computeroutput> format specifies the
      addend right there in the relocation.</para>
      <para>The trade offs of each approach should be clear.  With
      <computeroutput>REL</computeroutput> you need to do an extra
      memory reference to find the addend before the fixup, but you
      don't waste space in the binary because you use relocation
      target memory.  With <computeroutput>RELA</computeroutput> you
      keep the addend with the relocation, but waste that space in the
      on disk binary.  Most modern systems use
      <computeroutput>RELA</computeroutput> relocations.</para>
      <section>
        <info>
          <title>Relocations in action</title>
        </info>
        <para>The example below shows how relocations work.  We create
	two very simple shared libraries and reference one from in the
	other.</para>
        <example>
          <info>
            <title>Specifying Dynamic Libraries</title>
          </info>
          <programlisting linenumbering="numbered"><xi:include href="code/relocs.txt" parse="text"/></programlisting>
        </example>
        <para>We thus have one relocation in
	<computeroutput>addendtest.so</computeroutput> of type
	<computeroutput>R_IA64_DIR64LSB</computeroutput>.  If you look
	this up in the IA64 ABI, the acronym can be broken down to
	</para>
        <orderedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis>R_IA64</emphasis> : all relocations start with this prefix.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis>DIR64</emphasis> : a 64 bit direct type relocation</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis>LSB</emphasis> : Since IA64 can operate in big and
	    little endian modes, this relocation is little endian
	    (least significant byte).</para>
          </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
        <para>The ABI continues to say that that relocation means "the
        value of the symbol pointed to by the relocation, plus any
        addend".  We can see we have an addend of 8, since
        <computeroutput>sizeof(int) == 4</computeroutput> and we have
        moved two int's into the array (<computeroutput>*j = i +
        2</computeroutput>).  So at runtime, to fix this relocation
        you need to find the address of symbol
        <computeroutput>i</computeroutput> and put its value, plus 8
        into <computeroutput>0x104f8</computeroutput>.</para>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section>
      <info>
        <title>Position Independence</title>
      </info>
      <para>In an <emphasis>executable</emphasis> file, the code and
    data segment is given a specified base address in virtual memory.
    The executable code is not shared, and each executable gets its
    own fresh address space.  This means that the compiler knows
    exactly where the data section will be, and can reference it
    directly.</para>
      <para>Libraries have no such guarantee.  They can know that their
    data section will be a specified <emphasis>offset</emphasis> from
    the base address; but exactly where that base address is can only
    be known at runtime.</para>
      <para>Consequently all libraries must be produced with code that
    can execute no matter where it is put into memory, known as
    <emphasis>position independent code</emphasis> (or PIC for short).
    Note that the data section is still a fixed offset from the code
    section; but to actually find the address of data the offset needs
    to be added to the load address.</para>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="global_offset_tables">
    <info>
      <title>Global Offset Tables</title>
    </info>
    <para>You might have noticed a critical problem with relocations
      when thinking about the goals of a shared library.  We mentioned
      previously that the big advantage of a shared library with
      virtual memory is that multiple programs can use the code in
      memory by sharing of pages.</para>
    <para>The problem stems from the fact that libraries have no
    guarantee about where they will be put into memory.  The dynamic
    linker will find the most convenient place in virtual memory for
    each library required and place it there.  Think about the
    alternative if this were <emphasis>not</emphasis> to happen; every
    library in the system would require its own chunk of virtual
    memory so that no two overlapped.  Every time a new library were
    added to the system it would require allocation.  Someone could
    potentially be a hog and write a <emphasis>huge</emphasis>
    library, not leaving enough space for other libraries!  And
    chances are, your program doesn't ever want to use that library
    anyway.</para>
    <para>Thus, if you modify the code of a shared library with a
      relocation, that code no longer becomes sharable.  We've lost
      the advantage of our shared library.</para>
    <para>Below we explain the mechanism for doing this.</para>
    <section>
      <info>
        <title>The Global Offset Table</title>
      </info>
      <para>So imagine the situation where we take the value of a
      symbol.  With only relocations, we would have the dynamic linker
      look up the memory address of that symbol and re-write the code
      to load that address.</para>
      <para>A fairly straight forward enhancement would be to set aside
      space in our binary to hold the address of that symbol, and have
      the dynamic linker put the address there rather than in the code
      directly.  This way we never need to touch the code part of the
      binary.</para>
      <para>The area that is set aside for these addresses is called
      the Global Offset Table, or GOT.  The GOT lives in a section of
      the ELF file called <computeroutput>.got</computeroutput>.
      </para>
      <figure>
        <info>
          <title>Memory access via the GOT</title>
        </info>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="chapter08/figures/got-plt.eps" format="EPS"/>
          </imageobject>
          <imageobject role="fo">
            <imagedata fileref="figures/got-plt.svg" format="SVG" scalefit="1" width="100%" contentdepth="100%"/>
          </imageobject>
          <imageobject role="html">
            <imagedata fileref="chapter08/figures/got-plt.png" format="PNG"/>
          </imageobject>
          <textobject>
            <phrase>To keep code (green) sharable, we define process
	    private areas to which we can store the addresses of
	    common variables.  This allows us to load the code
	    anywhere in the process address space whilst still sharing
	    the underlying physical pages.</phrase>
          </textobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
      <para>The GOT is private to each process, and the process must
      have write permissions to it.  Conversely the library code is
      shared and the process should have only read and execute
      permissions on the code; it would be a serious security breach
      if the process could modify code.</para>
      <section>
        <info>
          <title>The GOT in action</title>
        </info>
        <example>
          <info>
            <title>Using the GOT</title>
          </info>
          <programlisting linenumbering="numbered"><xi:include href="code/got.txt" parse="text"/></programlisting>
        </example>
        <para>Above we create a simple shared library which refers to
	an external symbol.  We do not know the address of this symbol
	at compile time, so we leave it for the dynamic linker to fix
	up at runtime.</para>
        <para>But we want our code to remain sharable, in case other
	processes want to use our code as well.</para>
        <para>The disassembly reveals just how we do this with the
	<computeroutput>.got</computeroutput>.  On IA64 (the
	architecture which the library was compiled for) the register
	<computeroutput>r1</computeroutput> is known as the
	<emphasis>global pointer</emphasis> and always points to where
	the <computeroutput>.got</computeroutput> section is loaded
	into memory.</para>
        <para>If we have a look at the
	<computeroutput>readelf</computeroutput> output we can see
	that the <computeroutput>.got</computeroutput> section starts
	0x10570 bytes past where library was loaded into memory.  Thus
	if the library were to be loaded into memory at address
	0x6000000000000000 the <computeroutput>.got</computeroutput>
	would be at 0x6000000000010570, and register
	<computeroutput>r1</computeroutput> would always point to this
	address.</para>
        <para>Working backwards through the disassembly, we can see
	that we store the value 100 into the memory address held in
	register <computeroutput>r15</computeroutput>.  If we look
	back we can see that register 15 holds the value of the memory
	address stored in register 14.  Going back one more step, we
	see we load this address is found by adding a small number to
	register 1.  The GOT is simply a big long list of entries, one
	for each external variable.  This means that the GOT entry for
	the external variable <computeroutput>i</computeroutput> is
	stored 24 bytes (that is 3 64 bit addresses).
	</para>
        <example>
          <info>
            <title>Relocations against the GOT</title>
          </info>
          <programlisting linenumbering="numbered"><xi:include href="code/got-relocs.txt" parse="text"/></programlisting>
        </example>
        <para>We can also check out the relocation for this entry too.
	The relocation says "replace the value at offset 10588 with
	the memory location that symbol i is stored at".</para>
        <para>We know that the <computeroutput>.got</computeroutput>
	starts at offset 0x10570 from the previous output.  We have
	also seen how the code loads an address 0x18 (24 in decimal)
	past this, giving us an address of 0x10570 + 0x18 =
	0x10588 ... the address which the relocation is for!</para>
        <para>So before the program begins, the dynamic linker will
	have fixed up the relocation to ensure that the value of the
	memory at offset 0x10588 is the address of the global variable
	<computeroutput>i</computeroutput>!</para>
      </section>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="dynamic_libraries">
    <info>
      <title>Libraries</title>
    </info>
    <section>
      <info>
        <title>The Procedure Lookup Table</title>
      </info>
      <para>Libraries may contain many functions, and a program may
      end up including many libraries to get its work done.  A program
      may only use one or two functions from each library of the many
      available, and depending on the run-time path through the code
      may use some functions and not others.</para>
      <para>As we have seen, the process of dynamic linking is a
      fairly computationally intensive one, since it involves looking
      up and searching through many tables.  Anything that can be done
      to reduce the overheads will increase performance.</para>
      <para>The Procedure Lookup Table (PLT) facilitates what is
      called <emphasis>lazy binding</emphasis> in programs.  Binding
      is synonymous with the fix-up process described above for
      variables located in the GOT.  When an entry has been "fixed-up"
      it is said to be "bound" to its real address.</para>
      <para>As we mentioned, sometimes a program will include a
      function from a library but never actually call that function,
      depending on user input.  The process of binding this function
      is quite intensive, involving loading code, searching through
      tables and writing memory.  To go through the process of binding
      a function that is not used is simply a waste of time.</para>
      <para>Lazy binding defers this expense until the actual function
      is called by using a PLT.</para>
      <para>Each library function has an entry in the PLT, which
      initially points to some special dummy code.  When the program
      calls the function, it actually calls the PLT entry (in the same
      was as variables are referenced through the GOT).</para>
      <para>This dummy function will load a few parameters that need
      to be passed to the dynamic linker for it to resolve the
      function and then call into a special lookup function of the
      dynamic linker.  The dynamic linker finds the real address of
      the function, and writes that location into the calling
      binary over the top of the dummy function call.</para>
      <para>Thus, the next time the function is called the address can
      be loaded without having to go back into the dynamic loader
      again.  If a function is never called, then the PLT entry will
      never be modified but there will be no runtime overhead.</para>
      <section>
        <info>
          <title>The PLT in action</title>
        </info>
        <para>Things start to get a bit hairy here!  If nothing else,
	you should begin to appreciate that there is a fair bit of
	work in resolving a dynamic symbol!</para>
        <para>Let us consider the simple "hello World" application.
	This will only make one library call to
	<computeroutput>printf</computeroutput> to output the
	string to the user.</para>
        <example>
          <info>
            <title>Hello World PLT example</title>
          </info>
          <programlisting linenumbering="numbered">
            <xi:include href="code/hello.txt" parse="text"/>
          </programlisting>
        </example>
        <para>We can see above that we have a
	<computeroutput>R_IA64_IPLTLSB</computeroutput> relocation for
	our <computeroutput>printf</computeroutput> symbol.  This is
	saying "put the address of symbol printf into memory address
	0x6000000000000f10".  We have to start digging deeper to find
	the exact procedure that gets us the function.</para>
        <para>Below we have a look at the disassembly of the
	<computeroutput>main()</computeroutput> function of the
	program.</para>
        <example>
          <info>
            <title>Hello world main()</title>
          </info>
          <programlisting linenumbering="numbered">
            <xi:include href="code/hello-main-dis.txt" parse="text"/>
          </programlisting>
        </example>
        <para>The call to 0x4000000000000520 must be us calling the
	<computeroutput>printf</computeroutput> function.  We can find
	out where this is by looking at the sections with
	<computeroutput>readelf</computeroutput>.</para>
        <example>
          <info>
            <title>Hello world sections</title>
          </info>
          <programlisting linenumbering="numbered">
            <xi:include href="code/hello-sections.txt" parse="text"/>
          </programlisting>
        </example>
        <para>That address is (unsurprisingly) in the
	<computeroutput>.plt</computeroutput> section.  So there we
	have our call into the PLT! But we're not satisfied with that,
	let's keep digging further to see what we can uncover.  We
	disassemble the <computeroutput>.plt</computeroutput>
	section to see what that call actually does.</para>
        <example>
          <info>
            <title>Hello world PLT</title>
          </info>
          <programlisting linenumbering="numbered">
            <xi:include href="code/hello-plt.txt" parse="text"/>
          </programlisting>
        </example>
        <para>Let us step through the instructions.  Firstly, we add
	80 to the value in r1, storing it in r15.  We know from before
	that r1 will be pointing to the GOT, so this is saying "store
	in r15 80 bytes into the GOT".  The next thing we do is load
	into r16 the value stored in this location in the GOT, and
	post increment the value in r15 by 8 bytes.  We then store r1
	(the location of the GOT) in r14 and set r1 to be the value in
	the next 8 bytes after r15.  Then we branch to r16.</para>
        <para>In the previous chapter we discussed how functions are
	actually called through a function descriptor which contains
	the function address and the address of the global pointer.
	Here we can see that the PLT entry is first loading the
	function value, moving on 8 bytes to the second part of the
	function descriptor and then loading that value into the op
	register before calling the function.</para>
        <para>But what exactly are we loading?  We know that r1 will
	be pointing to the GOT.  We go 80 bytes past the got
	(0x50)</para>
        <example>
          <info>
            <title>Hello world GOT</title>
          </info>
          <programlisting linenumbering="numbered">
            <xi:include href="code/hello-got.txt" parse="text"/>
          </programlisting>
        </example>
        <para>0x6000000000000ec0 + 0x50 = 0x6000000000000f10, or the
	<computeroutput>.IA_64.pltoff</computeroutput> section.  Now
	we're starting to get somewhere!</para>
        <para>We can decode the <application>objdump</application>
	output so we can see exactly what is being loaded here.
	Swapping the byte order of the first 8 bytes
	<computeroutput>f0 04 00 00 00 00 00 40</computeroutput> we
	end up with
	<computeroutput>0x4000000000004f0</computeroutput>.  Now that
	address looks familiar!  Looking back up at the assemble
	output of the PLT we see that address.</para>
        <para>The code at
	<computeroutput>0x4000000000004f0</computeroutput> firstly
	puts a zero value into r15, and then branches back to
	<computeroutput>0x40000000000004c0</computeroutput>.  Wait a
	minute!  That's the start of our PLT section.</para>
        <para>We can trace this code through too.  Firstly we save the
	value of the global pointer
	(<computeroutput>r2</computeroutput>) then we load three 8
	byte values into <computeroutput>r16</computeroutput>,
	<computeroutput>r17</computeroutput> and finally,
	<computeroutput>r1</computeroutput>.  We then branch to the
	address in <computeroutput>r17</computeroutput>.  What we are
	seeing here is the actual call into the dynamic linker!</para>
        <para>We need to delve into the ABI to understand exactly what
	is being loaded at this point.  The ABI says two things --
	dynamically linked programs must have a special section
	(called the
	<computeroutput>DT_IA_64_PLT_RESERVE</computeroutput> section)
	that can hold three 8 byte values.  There is a pointer where
	this reserved area in the dynamic segment of the binary.</para>
        <example>
          <info>
            <title>Dynamic Segment</title>
          </info>
          <programlisting linenumbering="numbered">
            <xi:include href="code/hello-dynamic.txt" parse="text"/>
          </programlisting>
        </example>
        <para>Do you notice anything about it?  Its the same value as
	the GOT.  This means that the first three 8 byte entries in
	the GOT are actually the reserved area; thus will always be
	pointed to by the global pointer.</para>
        <para>When the dynamic linker starts it is its duty to fill
	these values in.  The ABI says that the first value will be
	filled in by the dynamic linker giving this
	<emphasis>module</emphasis> a unique ID.  The second value is
	the global pointer value for the dynamic linker, and the third
	value is the address of the function that finds and fixes up
	the symbol.</para>
        <example>
          <info>
            <title>Code in the dynamic linker for setting up special
	  values
	  (from libc <computeroutput>sysdeps/ia64/dl-machine.h</computeroutput>)</title>
          </info>
          <programlisting linenumbering="numbered" language="c">
            <xi:include href="code/runtime_setup.c" parse="text"/>
          </programlisting>
        </example>
        <para>We can see how this gets setup by the dynamic linker by
	looking at the function that does this for the binary.  The
	<computeroutput>reserve</computeroutput> variable is set from
	the PLT_RESERVE section pointer in the binary.  The unique
	value (put into <computeroutput>reserve[0]</computeroutput>)
	is the address of the <emphasis>link map</emphasis> for this
	object.  Link maps are the internal representation within
	<computeroutput>glibc</computeroutput> for shared objects.  We
	then put in the address of
	<computeroutput>_dl_runtime_resolve</computeroutput> to the
	second value (assuming we are not using profiling).
	<computeroutput>reserve[2]</computeroutput> is finally set to
	gp, which has been found from r2 with the
	<computeroutput>__asm__</computeroutput> call.</para>
        <para>Looking back at the ABI, we see that the
	<computeroutput>relocation index</computeroutput> for the
	entry must be placed in <computeroutput>r15</computeroutput>
	and the unique identifier must be passed in
	<computeroutput>r16</computeroutput>.</para>
        <para><computeroutput>r15</computeroutput> has previously been
	set in the stub code, before we jumped back to the start of
	the PLT.  Have a look down the entries, and notice how each
	PLT entry loads <computeroutput>r15</computeroutput> with an
	incremented value?  It should come as no surprise if you look
	at the relocations the <computeroutput>printf</computeroutput>
	relocation is number zero.</para>
        <para><computeroutput>r16</computeroutput> we load up from the
	values that have been initialised by the dynamic linker, as
	previously discussed.  Once that is ready, we can load the
	function address and global pointer and branch into the
	function.</para>
        <para>What happens at this point is the dynamic linker
	function <computeroutput>_dl_runtime_resolve</computeroutput>
	is run.  It finds the relocation; remember how the relocation
	specified the name of the symbol?  It uses this name to find
	the right function; this might involve loading the library
	from disk if it is not already in memory, or otherwise sharing
	the code.</para>
        <para>The relocation record provides the dynamic linker with
	the address it needs to "fix up"; remember it was in the GOT
	and loaded by the initial PLT stub?  This means that after the
	first time the function is called, the
	<emphasis>second</emphasis> time it is loaded it will get the
	direct address of the function; short circuiting the dynamic
	linker.</para>
      </section>
      <section>
        <info>
          <title>Summary</title>
        </info>
        <para>You've seen the <emphasis>exact</emphasis> mechanism
	behind the PLT, and consequently the inner workings of the
	dynamic linker.  The important points to remember are</para>
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Library calls in your program actually call a stub
	      of code in the PLT of the binary.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>That stub code loads an address and jumps to
	      it.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Initially, that address points to a function in
	      the dynamic linker which is capable of looking up the
	      "real" function, given the information in the relocation
	      entry for that function.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>The dynamic linker re-writes the address that the
	      stub code reads, so that the next time the function is
	      called it will go straight to the right address.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </section>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="libraries_and_the_linker">
    <info>
      <title>Working with libraries and the linker</title>
    </info>
    <para>The presence of the dynamic linker provides both some
    advantages we can utilise and some extra issues that need to be
    resolved to get a functional system.</para>
    <section>
      <info>
        <title>Library versions</title>
      </info>
      <para>One potential issue is different versions of libraries.
      With only static libraries there is much less potential for
      problems, as all library code is built directly into the binary
      of the application.  If you want to use a new version of the
      library you need to recompile it into a new binary, replacing
      the old one.</para>
      <para>This is obviously fairly impractical for common libraries,
      the most common of course being <application>libc</application>
      which is included in most all applications.  If it were only
      available as a static library any change would require every
      single application in the system be rebuilt.</para>
      <para>However, changes in the way the dynamic library work could
      cause multiple problems.  In the best case, the modifications
      are completely compatible and nothing externally visible is
      changed.  On the other hand the changes might cause the
      application to crash; for example if a function that used to
      take an <computeroutput>int</computeroutput> changes to take an
      <computeroutput>int *</computeroutput>.  Worse, the new library
      version could have changed semantics and suddenly start silently
      returning different, possibly wrong values.  This can be a very
      nasty bug to try and track down; when an application crashes you
      can use a debugger to isolate where the error occurs whilst data
      corruption or modification may only show up in seemingly
      unrelated parts of the application.</para>
      <para>The dynamic linker requires a way to determine the version
      of libraries within the system so that newer revisions can be
      identified.  There are a number of schemes a modern dynamic
      linker can use to find the right versions of libraries.</para>
      <section>
        <info>
          <title>
            <computeroutput>sonames</computeroutput>
          </title>
        </info>
        <para>Using <computeroutput>sonames</computeroutput> we can
	add some extra information to a library to help identify
	versions.</para>
        <para>As we have seen previously, an application lists the
	libraries it requires in
	<computeroutput>DT_NEEDED</computeroutput> fields in the
	dynamic section of the binary.  The actual library is held in
	a file on disc, usually in
	<computeroutput>/lib</computeroutput> for core system
	libraries or <computeroutput>/usr/lib</computeroutput> for
	optional libraries.</para>
        <para>To allow multiple versions of the library to exist on
	disk, they obviously require differing file names.  The
	<computeroutput>soname</computeroutput> scheme uses a
	combination of names and file system links to build a
	hierarchy of libraries.</para>
        <para>This is done by introducing the concept of
	<emphasis>major</emphasis> and <emphasis>minor</emphasis>
	library revisions.  A minor revision is one wholly backwards
	compatible with a previous version of the library; this
	usually consists of only bug fixes.  A major revision is
	therefore any revision that is not compatible; e.g. changes
	the inputs to functions or the way a function behaves.</para>
        <para>As each library revision, major or minor, will need to
	be kept in a separate file on disk, this forms the basis of
	the library hierarchy.  The library name is by convention
	<computeroutput>libNAME.so.MAJOR.MINOR</computeroutput><footnote><para>You can optionally have a <emphasis>release</emphasis>
	as a final identifier after the minor number.  Generally this
	is enough to distinguish all the various versions
	library.</para></footnote>.  However, if every application
	were directly linked against this file we would have the same
	issue as with a static library; every time a minor change
	happened we would need to rebuild the application to point to
	the new library.</para>
        <para>What we really want to refer to is the
	<emphasis>major</emphasis> number of the library.  If this
	changes, we reasonably are required to recompile our
	application, since we need to make sure our program is still
	compatible with the new library.</para>
        <para>Thus the <computeroutput>soname</computeroutput> is the
	<computeroutput>libNAME.so.MAJOR</computeroutput>.  The
	<computeroutput>soname</computeroutput> should be set in the
	<computeroutput>DT_SONAME</computeroutput> field of the
	dynamic section in a shared library; the library author can
	specify this version when they build the library.</para>
        <para>Thus each minor version library file on disc can specify
	 the same major version number in it's
	 <computeroutput>DT_SONAME</computeroutput> field, allowing
	 the dynamic linker to know that this particular library file
	 implements a particular major revision of the library API and
	 ABI.</para>
        <para>To keep track of this, an application called
	<application>ldconfig</application> is commonly run to create
	symbolic links named for the major version to the latest minor
	version on the system.  <application>ldconfig</application>
	works by running through all the libraries that implement a
	particular major revision number, and then picks out the one
	with the highest minor revision.  It then creates a symbolic
	link from <computeroutput>libNAME.so.MAJOR</computeroutput> to
	the actual library file on disc,
	i.e. <computeroutput>libNAME.so.MAJOR.MINOR</computeroutput>.</para>
        <para>XXX : talk about libtool versions</para>
        <para>The final piece of the hierarchy is the
	<emphasis>compile name</emphasis> for the library.  When you
	compile your program, to link against a library you use the
	<computeroutput>-lNAME</computeroutput> flag, which goes off
	searching for the <computeroutput>libNAME.so</computeroutput>
	file in the library search path.  Notice however, we have not
	specified any version number; we just want to link against the
	latest library on the system.  It is up to the installation
	procedure for the library to create the symbolic link between
	the compile <computeroutput>libNAME.so</computeroutput> name
	and the latest library code on the system.  Usually this is
	handled by your package management system
	(<application>dpkg</application> or
	<application>rpm</application>).  This is not an automated
	process because it is possible that the latest library on the
	system may not be the one you wish to always compile against;
	for example if the latest installed library were a development
	version not appropriate for general use.</para>
        <para>The general process is illustrated below.</para>
        <figure>
          <info>
            <title>
              <computeroutput>sonames</computeroutput>
            </title>
          </info>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="chapter08/figures/libs.eps" format="EPS"/>
            </imageobject>
            <imageobject role="fo">
              <imagedata fileref="figures/libs.svg" format="SVG" scalefit="1" width="100%" contentdepth="100%"/>
            </imageobject>
            <imageobject role="html">
              <imagedata fileref="chapter08/figures/libs.png" format="PNG"/>
            </imageobject>
            <textobject>
              <phrase>Describing the soname system</phrase>
            </textobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>
        <section>
          <info>
            <title>How the dynamic linker looks up libraries</title>
          </info>
          <para>When the application starts, the dynamic linker looks
	  at the <computeroutput>DT_NEEDED</computeroutput> field to
	  find the required libraries.  This field contains the
	  <computeroutput>soname</computeroutput> of the library, so
	  the next step is for the dynamic linker to walk through all
	  the libraries in its search path looking for it.</para>
          <para>This process conceptually involves two steps.  Firstly
	  the dynamic linker needs to search through all the libraries
	  to find those that implement the given
	  <computeroutput>soname</computeroutput>.  Secondly the file
	  names for the minor revisions need to be compared to find
	  the latest version, which is then ready to be loaded.</para>
          <para>We mentioned previously that there is a symbolic link
	  setup by <application>ldconfig</application> between the
	  library <computeroutput>soname</computeroutput> and the
	  latest minor revision.  Thus the dynamic linker should need
	  to only follow that link to find the correct file to load,
	  rather than having to open all possible libraries and decide
	  which one to go with each time the application is
	  required.</para>
          <para>Since file system access is so slow,
	  <application>ldconfig</application> also creates a
	  <emphasis>cache</emphasis> of libraries installed in the
	  system.  This cache is simply a list of
	  <computeroutput>soname</computeroutput>s of libraries
	  available to the dynamic linker and a pointer to the major
	  version link on disk, saving the dynamic linker having to
	  read entire directories full of files to locate the correct
	  link.  You can analyse this with <application>/sbin/ldconfig
	  -p</application>; it actually lives in the file
	  <computeroutput>/etc/ldconfig.so.cache</computeroutput>.  If
	  the library is not found in the cache the dynamic linker
	  will fall back to the slower option of walking the file
	  system, thus it is important to re-run
	  <application>ldconfig</application> when new libraries are
	  installed.</para>
        </section>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section>
      <info>
        <title>Finding symbols</title>
      </info>
      <para>We've already discussed how the dynamic linker gets the
      address of a library function and puts it in the PLT for the
      program to use.  But so far we haven't discussed just
      <emphasis>how</emphasis> the dynamic linker finds the address of
      the function.  The whole process is called
      <emphasis>binding</emphasis>, because the symbol name is bound
      to the address it represents.</para>
      <para>The dynamic linker has a few pieces of information;
      firstly the <emphasis>symbol</emphasis> that it is searching
      for, and secondly a list of libraries that that symbol might be
      in, as defined by the <computeroutput>DT_NEEDED</computeroutput>
      fields in the binary.</para>
      <para>Each shared object library has a section, marked
      <computeroutput>SHT_DYNSYM</computeroutput> and called
      <computeroutput>.dynsym</computeroutput> which is the minimal
      set of symbols required for dynamic linking -- that is any
      symbol in the library that may be called by an external
      program.</para>
      <section>
        <info>
          <title>Dynamic Symbol Table</title>
        </info>
        <para>In fact, there are three sections that all play a part
	in describing the dynamic symbols.  Firstly, let us look at
	the definition of a symbol from the ELF specification</para>
        <example>
          <info>
            <title>Symbol definition from ELF</title>
          </info>
          <programlisting linenumbering="numbered"><xi:include href="code/symbol.txt" parse="text"/></programlisting>
        </example>
        <table>
          <info>
            <title>ELF symbol fields</title>
          </info>
          <tgroup cols="2">
            <thead>
              <row>
                <entry>Field</entry>
                <entry>Value</entry>
              </row>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
              <row>
                <entry>
                  <computeroutput>st_name</computeroutput>
                </entry>
                <entry>An <emphasis>index to the string table</emphasis></entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>
                  <computeroutput>st_value</computeroutput>
                </entry>
                <entry>Value - in a
		relocatable shared object this holds the offset from
		the section of index given in
		<computeroutput>st_shndx</computeroutput></entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>
                  <computeroutput>st_size</computeroutput>
                </entry>
                <entry>Any associated size of the symbol</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>
                  <computeroutput>st_info</computeroutput>
                </entry>
                <entry>Information on the binding of the symbol
		(described below) and what type of symbol this is (a
		function, object, etc).</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>
                  <computeroutput>st_other</computeroutput>
                </entry>
                <entry>Not currently used</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>
                  <computeroutput>st_shndx</computeroutput>
                </entry>
                <entry>Index of the section this symbol resides in
		(see <computeroutput>st_value</computeroutput></entry>
              </row>
            </tbody>
          </tgroup>
        </table>
        <para>As you can see, the actual string of the symbol name is
	held in a separate section
	(<computeroutput>.dynstr</computeroutput>; the entry in the
	<computeroutput>.dynsym</computeroutput> section only holds an
	index into the string section.  This creates some level of
	overhead for the dynamic linker; the dynamic linker must read
	all of the symbol entries in the
	<computeroutput>.dynsym</computeroutput> section and then
	follow the index pointer to find the symbol name for
	comparison.
	</para>
        <para>To speed this process up, a third section called
	<computeroutput>.hash</computeroutput> is introduced,
	containing a <emphasis>hash table</emphasis> of symbol names
	to symbol table entries.  This hash table is pre-computed when
	the library is built and allows the dynamic linker to find the
	symbol entry much faster, generally with only one or two
	lookups.</para>
      </section>
      <section>
        <info>
          <title>Symbol Binding</title>
        </info>
        <para>Whilst we usually say the process of finding the address
	of a symbol refers is the process of binding that symbol, the
	<emphasis>symbol binding</emphasis> has a separate
	meaning.</para>
        <para>The binding of a symbol dictates its external visibility
	during the dynamic linking process.  A
	<emphasis>local</emphasis> symbol is not visible outside the
	object file it is defined in.  A <emphasis>global</emphasis>
	symbol is visible to other object files, and can satisfy
	undefined references in other objects.</para>
        <para>A <emphasis>weak</emphasis> reference is a special type
	of lower priority global reference.  This means it is designed
	to be overridden, as we will see shortly.</para>
        <para>Below we have an example C program which we analyse to
	inspect the symbol bindings.</para>
        <example>
          <info>
            <title>Examples of symbol bindings</title>
          </info>
          <programlisting linenumbering="numbered"><xi:include href="code/bindings.txt" parse="text"/></programlisting>
        </example>
        <para>Notice the use of
	<computeroutput>#pragma</computeroutput> to define the weak
	symbol.  A <computeroutput>pragma</computeroutput> is a way of
	communicating extra information to the compiler; its use is
	not common but occasionally is required to get the compiler to
	do out of the ordinary operations.x</para>
        <para>We inspect the symbols with two different tools; in both
	cases the binding is shown in the second column; the codes
	should be quite straight forward (are are documented in the
	tools <application>man</application> page).</para>
        <section>
          <info>
            <title>Overriding symbols</title>
          </info>
          <para>It is often very useful for a programmer to be able to
	  <emphasis>override</emphasis> a symbol in a library; that is
	  to subvert the normal symbol with a different
	  definition.</para>
          <para>We mentioned that the order that libraries is searched
	  is given by the order of the
	  <computeroutput>DT_NEEDED</computeroutput> fields within the
	  library.  However, it is possible to insert libraries as the
	  <emphasis>last</emphasis> libraries to be searched; this
	  means that any symbols within them will be found as the
	  final reference.</para>
          <para>This is done via an environment variable called
	  <computeroutput>LD_PRELOAD</computeroutput> which specifies
	  libraries that the linker should load last.</para>
          <example>
            <info>
              <title>Example of <computeroutput>LD_PRELOAD</computeroutput></title>
            </info>
            <programlisting linenumbering="numbered"><xi:include href="code/ld_preload.txt" parse="text"/></programlisting>
          </example>
          <para>In the above example we override the
	  <computeroutput>getpid</computeroutput> function to print
	  out a small statement when it is called.  We use the
	  <computeroutput>dlysm</computeroutput> function provided by
	  <computeroutput>libc</computeroutput> with an argument
	  telling it to continue on and find the
	  <emphasis>next</emphasis> symbol called
	  <computeroutput>getpid</computeroutput>.</para>
          <section>
            <info>
              <title>Weak symbols over time</title>
            </info>
            <para>The concept of the <emphasis>weak</emphasis> symbol
	  is that the symbol is marked as a lower priority and can be
	  overridden by another symbol.  Only if no other
	  implementation is found will the weak symbol be the one that
	  it used.</para>
            <para>The logical extension of this for the dynamic loader
	    is that all libraries should be loaded, and any weak
	    symbols in those libraries should be ignored for normal
	    symbols in any other library.  This was indeed how weak
	    symbol handling was originally implemented in Linux by
	    <application>glibc</application>.</para>
            <para>However, this was actually incorrect to the letter
	    of the Unix standard at the time
	    (<emphasis>SysVr4</emphasis>).  The standard actually
	    dictates that weak symbols should only be handled by the
	    <emphasis>static</emphasis> linker; they should remain
	    irrelevant to the dynamic linker (see the section on
	    binding order below).</para>
            <para>At the time, the Linux implementation of making the
	    dynamic linker override weak symbols matched with SGI's
	    IRIX platform, but differed to others such as Solaris and
	    AIX.  When the developers realised this behaviour
	    violated the standard it was reversed, and the old
	    behaviour relegated to requiring a special environment
	    flag (<emphasis>LD_DYNAMIC_WEAK</emphasis>) be set.</para>
          </section>
        </section>
        <section>
          <info>
            <title>Specifying binding order</title>
          </info>
          <para>We have seen how we can override a function in another
	  library by <emphasis>preloading</emphasis> another shared
	  library with the same symbol defined.  The symbol that gets
	  resolved as the final one is the last one in the order that
	  the dynamic loader loads the libraries.</para>
          <para>Libraries are loaded in the order they are specified
	  in the <computeroutput>DT_NEEDED</computeroutput> flag of
	  the binary.  This in turn is decided from the order that
	  libraries are passed in on the command line when the object
	  is built.  When symbols are to be located, the dynamic
	  linker starts at the last loaded library and works backwards
	  until the symbol is found.</para>
          <para>Some shared libraries, however, need a way to override
	  this behaviour.  They need to say to the dynamic linker
	  "look first inside me for these symbols, rather than working
	  backwards from the last loaded library".  Libraries can set
	  the <computeroutput>DT_SYMBOLIC</computeroutput> flag in
	  their dynamic section header to get this behaviour (this is
	  usually set by passing the
	  <computeroutput>-Bsymbolic</computeroutput> flag on the
	  static linkers command line when building the shared
	  library).</para>
          <para>What this flag is doing is controlling <emphasis>symbol
	  visibility</emphasis>.  The symbols in the library can not
	  be overridden so could be considered private to the library
	  that is being loaded.</para>
          <para>However, this loses a lot of granularity since the
	  library is either flagged for this behaviour, or it is not.
	  A better system would allow us to make some symbols private
	  and some symbols public.</para>
        </section>
        <section>
          <info>
            <title>Symbol Versioning</title>
          </info>
          <para>That better system comes from symbol versioning.  With
	  symbol versioning we specify some extra input to the static
	  linker to give it some more information about the symbols in
	  our shared library.</para>
          <example>
            <info>
              <title>Example of symbol versioning</title>
            </info>
            <programlisting linenumbering="numbered"><xi:include href="code/symbolver.txt" parse="text"/></programlisting>
          </example>
          <para>In the simplest case as above, we simply state if the
	  symbol is <emphasis>global</emphasis> or
	  <emphasis>local</emphasis>.  Thus in the case above the
	  <computeroutput>foo</computeroutput> function is most likely
	  a support function for
	  <computeroutput>test_foo</computeroutput>; whilst we are
	  happy for the overall functionality of the
	  <computeroutput>test_foo</computeroutput> function to be
	  overridden, if we do use the shared library version it needs
	  to have unaltered access nobody should modify the support
	  function.</para>
          <para>This allows us to keep our
	  <emphasis>namespace</emphasis> better organised.  Many
	  libraries might want to implement something that could be
	  named like a common function like
	  <computeroutput>read</computeroutput> or
	  <computeroutput>write</computeroutput>; however if they all
	  did the actual version given to the program might be
	  completely wrong.  By specifying symbols as
	  <emphasis>local</emphasis> only the developer can be sure
	  that nothing will conflict with that internal name, and
	  conversely the name he chose will not influence any other
	  program.</para>
          <para>An extension of this scheme is <emphasis>symbol
	  versioning</emphasis>.  With this you can specify multiple
	  versions of the same symbol in the same library.  The static
	  linker appends some version information after the symbol
	  name (something like <computeroutput>@VER</computeroutput>)
	  describing what version the symbol is given.</para>
          <para>If the developer implements a function that has the
	  same name but possibly a binary or programatically different
	  implementation he can increase the version number.  When new
	  applications are built against the shared library, they will
	  pick up the latest version of the symbol.  However,
	  applications built against earlier versions of the same
	  library will be requesting older versions (e.g. will have
	  older <computeroutput>@VER</computeroutput> strings in the
	  symbol name they request) and thus get the original
	  implementation. XXX : example</para>
        </section>
      </section>
    </section>
  </section>
</chapter>
